-=THE LAST FANTASY=-
荣誉出品
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
翻译：Lilycheng
校对：Lilycheng  NetAdmin
火星救援
阿西达利亚平原
全体注意
LEWIS ON RADIO: All right, team,
大家保持在视线之内
stay in sight of each other.
美国国家航天局 - 战神3号着陆点
完成使命，让航天局以你们为荣吧
Let's make NASA proud today.
第18个太阳日
你那边情况如何，沃特尼？
MARTINEZ: How's it looking over there, Watney?
既然你问了，很高兴告诉你
WATNEY: Well, you'll be happy to hear...
在14到28区内
that in Grid Section 14-28,
土壤微粒大部分都很粗糙
the particles were predominantly coarse...
但是，29区的土壤质量较好
but in 29, they're much finer...
应该可以用作化学分析
and they should be ideal for chem analysis.
哇哦，大家听到了吗？
MARTINEZ: Oh, wow. Did everybody hear that?
马克的重大发现是一堆烂泥
Mark just discovered dirt.
这事儿我们得通知媒体吧？
(LAUGHS) Should we alert the media?
你今天又做了什么，马丁内兹？
WATNEY: Sorry, what are you doing today, Martinez?
还是让飞行器立正站好吗？
Making sure the MAV is still upright?
我得让你知道
MARTINEZ: I'd like you to know
飞行设备的外观检查
that visual inspection of the equipment...
对任务成功执行至关重要
is imperative to mission success.
我还想让你知道，飞行器的确站的很直
I also would like to report that the MAV is still upright.
沃特尼
LEWIS: (SIGHS) Watney,
如果你无线电一直开着
you keep leaving your channel open...
马丁内兹就会一直找你说个不停
which leads to Martinez responding...
我们就都得听你俩闲扯
which leads to all of us listening...
再这样下去我就要发飙了
which leads to me being annoyed.
收到了
WATNEY: Roger that.
马丁内兹，队长希望你能闭上
Martinez, the captain would like you to please...
你那“能说会道”的嘴巴
shut your smart mouth.
(LAUGHING)
我们希望你能换个词
We'd prefer to use a different adjective
来形容马丁内兹的嘴巴
to describe Martinez's mouth. (WATNEY LAUGHING)
贝克这话是在讽刺我吗？
MARTINEZ: Did Beck just insult me?
第一，人家是贝克医生；第二，他确实是在讽刺你
WATNEY: "Dr. Beck." And yes.
队长，我很乐意把他们的无线电关掉
Happy to turn the radios off from here, Commander.
只要你下命令
Just say the word.
等等，约翰森
Wait, Johanssen.
执行任务时，不间断的通讯是…
Constant communication is the hallmark...
给他们关掉
Shut 'em off.
不要啊
(BEEPS) WATNEY: No.
不要这样对我
No. Excuse me.
我替家乡的小伙们向你道歉，沃格尔
LEWIS: I apologize for my countrymen, Vogel.
没关系
VOGEL: Accepted.
队长，我们需要多少样本？
How many samples do we need, Commander?
7个
LEWIS: Seven.
每个100克
100 grams each.
(ALARM BLARING)
任务有更新，是风暴预警
We have a mission update. A storm warning.
队长，你现在能回居住舱吗？
Commander, you should come inside.
有个东西需要你看一下
You're gonna want to see this.
是什么？
What is it?
风暴预警
JOHANSSEN: A storm warning.
我在今早的简报看过了
LEWIS: I saw that in this morning's briefing.
我们能在风暴到达前完成任务
We'll be inside before it hits.
是没错，但是他们提升了预警强度
Yeah, they upgraded their estimate.
情况要比之前糟的多
The storm's gonna be a lot worse.
马丁内兹，你那边情况如何？
LEWIS: Martinez, how does it look?
很不妙
MARTINEZ: Not good.
风暴直径1200公里，方向24.41度
"1,200 kilometers in diameter, bearing 24.41 degrees."
直冲我们而来
That's tracking right towards us.
根据当前风暴等级
"Based on current escalation,
风力可达约8600牛顿
"estimated force of 8,600 newtons."
我们最多能承受多大风力？
What's the abort force?
7500牛顿
7,500.
只要高于这个数值，飞行器就会侧倾
MARTINEZ: Anything more than that and the MAV could tip.
要取消任务吗？
Do we scrub?
准备撤离
Begin abort procedure.
预估数据会存在一定的误差
VOGEL: We are estimating with a margin of error.
我们可以等风暴过去
We could wait it out.
等风暴过去吧
WATNEY: Let's wait it out.
等等吧
Let's wait it out.
队长，你怎么说？
JOHANSSEN: Commander?
准备紧急撤离
Prep emergency departure.
队长？
WATNEY: Commander?
任务取消了，这是命令
LEWIS: We're scrubbed. That's an order.
马丁内兹，距发射还有多长时间？
Martinez, how long before take-off?
12分钟
12 minutes.
(ALARM BLARING)
能见度几乎为零
LEWIS: Visibility is almost zero.
如果有人失去联系
Anyone gets lost,
就通过遥测定位来找我
hone in on my suit's telemetry.
大家准备好没？
You ready?
准备好了
Ready.
(ALL GROAN)
队长，你没事吧？
WATNEY: Commander, are you okay?
我没事
I'm okay.
(WIND HOWLING)
(STRAINING)
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
队长，倾斜度已经达到10度
Commander, we're at 10 degrees,
到12.3度就会发生侧翻
and the MAV is gonna tip at 12.3.
嘿！我想我有办法阻止倾斜了
WATNEY: Hey! We might be able to keep the MAV from tipping.
什么办法？
How?
用通讯杆的电缆把飞行器…
Use the cables from the comms mast as guy-lines...
绑到探测车上
anchor it with the Rover's.
大家小心！
LEWIS: Watch out!
(WATNEY GROANS)
(SCREAMING)
沃特尼！
Watney!
警报，检测到宇航服破裂
FEMALE AUTOMATED VOICE: Warning. Suit breach detected.
发生什么事了？
What happened?
沃特尼被击中了
He was hit.
沃特尼，回答我
Watney, report.
在遥测失灵前
Before we lost telemetry,
他的失压警报也响了
his decompression alarm went off.
约翰森，他最后的位置在哪里？
LEWIS: Where did you last see him?
我不知道
I don't know where he is.
他的生命体征如何？
LEWIS: What are the vitals on his suit?
他掉线了
He's offline.
我们失去了和他的一切联系
BECK: A complete loss of signal on Watney.
- 贝克！- 怎么了？
VOGEL: Beck! Yeah.
宇航服失压，他能存活多久？
How long can he survive decompression?
不到一分钟
Less than a minute.
大家排好队，往西走
Line up, walk west.
他可能趴在地上，我们别错过他了
He may be prone. We don't wanna step over him.
队长
MARTINEZ: Commander...
倾斜度已经达到10.5度
We're at 10.5 degrees.
警报，严重倾斜
FEMALE AUTOMATED VOICE: Warning. Excessive tilt.
在风力作用下会继续倾斜到11度
Tilting to 11 with all the gusts of wind.
收到
Copy that.
所有人，定位马丁内兹的位置
Everyone, hone in on Martinez's suit.
你们回气密舱，准备发射
It'll get you to airlock. Get in, prep for launch.
那你呢，队长？
BECK: What about you, Commander?
我接着找，你们行动！
I'm gonna search a little longer. Get moving!
快！
Go!
沃特尼！
Watney!
沃特尼，听到请回答！
Watney, report!
飞行器现在倾斜11.6度
MARTINEZ: The MAV's at 11.6 degrees.
再来一阵强风就要倒了
One good gust and we're tipping.
如果撑不住了，你就发射
If it tips, you launch.
你真以为我会抛下你们吗？
You really think I'm gonna leave you behind?
这是命令，马丁内兹
LEWIS: That's an order, Martinez.
马克！
Mark! (BECK GRUNTING)
马克！能听到吗？
Mark! Can you hear me?
马丁内兹，近距雷达能派上用场吗？
Martinez, what about the proximity radar?
它能不能检测到沃特尼的位置？
Could that detect Watney's suit?
近距雷达是为了勘测赫尔墨斯号的
MARTINEZ: It's made to see the Hermes from orbit...
它可测不到宇航服上的一块小金属
not a little piece of metal from a single suit.
试一试
LEWIS: Give it a try.
收到
MARTINEZ: Roger.
她在干什么？
VOGEL: What is she thinking? She knows
她明知道红外线没法穿透风暴
the infrared can't get through a sandstorm.
她不会放弃任何一个希望
BECK: She's grasping for anything.
没有信号
MARTINEZ: We've got negative contact
近距雷达无法定位
on the proximity radar.
完全无法定位？
LEWIS: Nothing?
是的，就连居住舱都看不清
MARTINEZ: No. I can barely see the Hab.
队长，我知道你不想听这句话，但是…
Commander, I know you don't wanna hear this, but...
马克已经死了
Mark is dead.
队长！
Commander!
贝克，你说话不经大脑吗？
Hey, what the hell is wrong with you, man?
我的朋友刚刚去世
My friend just died.
我不想队长也遭遇不幸
I don't want my commander to die, too.
失衡警报
FEMALE AUTOMATED VOICE: Stability warning.
我们要侧倾了！
We're tipping!
队长，你现在就得回来！
BECK: Commander, you need to get back to the ship, now!
13度
MARTINEZ: 13 degrees.
如果失去平衡，我们就都完蛋了
If we pass balance, we'll never rock back.
我还剩一个办法
MARTINEZ: I've got one more trick left,
但接下来我就只能执行命令了，队长
and then I'm following orders, Commander.
你居然用燃料保持平衡？！
You're firing the OMS? (ALARM BEEPING)
没错
That's right.
队长！
Commander!
我回去了
LEWIS: On my way. (BREATHING HEAVILY)
约翰森，快上来
MARTINEZ: Johanssen, let's go.
(SIGHS)
(STRUGGLING)
马克！
LEWIS: Mark!
目前保持在11.5度
MARTINEZ: We're at 11.5 and holding.
发射准备就绪
Ready to go on your command.
准备发射
Ready to launch.
队长
Commander.
发射前我需要你的口头指令
I need you to verbally tell me whether or not to.
发射
Launch.
在中央标准时间
SANDERS ON TV: At around 4:30 a.m.
凌晨4点30分
Central Standard Time...
卫星检测到火星上有一场风暴
our satellites detected a storm
正在接近战神3号的任务执行地点
approaching the Ares 3 mission site on Mars.
到6点45分时，风暴情况已十分严峻
At 6:45, the storm had escalated to severe...
我们别无他法，只能取消任务
and we had no choice but to abort the mission.
多亏了队长刘易斯的领导
Thanks to the quick action of Commander Lewis...
宇航员贝克，约翰森，马丁内兹和沃格尔
astronauts Beck, Johanssen, Martinez and Vogel...
及时回到了火星飞行器
were all able to reach the Mars Ascent Vehicle...
并在7点28分完成了紧急撤退
and perform an emergency launch at 7:28 Central Time.
然而，在撤退过程中
Unfortunately, during the evacuation...
宇航员马克·沃特尼被碎片击中身亡
astronaut Mark Watney was struck by debris and killed.
(REPORTERS GASP) (CAMERAS CLICKING)
队长刘易斯和其他队员
Commander Lewis and the rest of her team...
成功和赫尔墨斯号对接
were able to intercept safely with the Hermes
正在返回地球
and are now heading home.
但是马克·沃特尼已经殉职
But Mark Watney is dead.
桑德斯局长！
FEMALE REPORTER: Director Sanders!
(REPORTERS CLAMORING)
(DEVICE BEEPING)
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
氧气含量过低
FEMALE AUTOMATED VOICE: Oxygen level critical.
Oxygen level critical.
(BEEPING CONTINUES)
氧气含量…
Oxygen level...
(BEEPING STOPS)
(GROANING)
(YELPS)
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
(GROANING)
(DOOR BEEPING)
(BUZZING)
舱压已稳定
FEMALE AUTOMATED VOICE: Pressure stable.
(BREATHING RAPIDLY)
(SCREAMING IN PAIN)
(GRUNTS)
(BREATHING RAPIDLY)
(EXHALES DEEPLY)
(GROANING)
(STAPLER CLATTERS)
(GROANS)
(EXHALING DEEPLY)
操
Fuck.
好了
Okay.
开始
Okay-
大家好，我是宇航员马克·沃特尼
Hello, this is Mark Watney, astronaut.
现在记录这些日志
I'm entering this log for the record...
是因为我不知道自己还能撑多久
in case I don't make it.
今天是第19个太阳日，时间6点53分
It is 06:53 on Sol 19...
我还活着
and I'm alive.
显而易见
Obviously.
但是这肯定会让我的队友们
But I'm guessing that's gonna come as a surprise
和航天局大吃一惊
to my crewmates and to NASA.
对世界来说也是重磅消息，所以…
And to the entire world, really, so...
惊喜吧
Surprise.
我没死在第18个太阳日
I did not die on Sol 18.
我的猜测是…
Best I can figure...
这根主通讯天线
this length of our primary communications antenna
断掉了
broke off...
刺穿了我的生命体征监测器
and tore through my bio-monitor. ..
还在我身上戳了个洞
And ripped a hole in me as well.
但是这截天线和流出的血
But the antenna and the blood, really,
却堵住了宇航服的缺口
managed to seal the breach in my suit...
让我活了下来
which kept me alive,
尽管队友们判断我已经去世了
even though the crew must have thought I was dead.
我无法联系宇航局
I have no way to contact NASA.
就算能联系上，下一次载人航天任务
And even if I could, it's gonna be four years...
也要等到四年以后
until a manned mission can reach me.
现在，我在一个只能住31天的居住舱里
And I'm in a Hab designed to last 31 days.
如果氧合器坏了，我会窒息而死
If the oxygenator breaks, I'm gonna suffocate.
如果水回收器坏了，我会渴死
If the water reclaimer breaks, I'll die of thirst.
如果居住舱坏了，我就会死于
If the Hab breaches, I'm just gonna, kind of...
内脏破裂
implode.
如果有奇迹，上面说的都不会发生
And if by some miracle, none of that happens...
我最后也会因为缺少食物而饿死
eventually I'm gonna run out of food.
所以…
So...
这就是我的处境
Yeah.
没错
(CLEARS THROAT)
(SIGHS)
(COMPUTER BEEPING)
我不能坐以待毙
I'm not gonna die here.
第21个太阳日
32...
33...
34...
35，36包
35, 36.
糖醋鸡
Sweet and sour chicken.
(GROANS SOFTLY)
(FLUSHING)
(WHIRRING)
瞧瞧这是什么？
What do we got?
马铃薯.
Solanum tuberosum.
(TYPING)
好了，我们来算算
Right, let's do the math.
我们此次任务预期为31个太阳日
Our surface mission here was supposed to last 31 sols.
为防万一，他们准备了68天的食物
For redundancy, they sent 68 sols worth of food.
而且是6个人的量
That's for 6 people.
所以对我来说，这些食物可以够吃300天
So for just me, that's gonna last 300 sols...
如果我每天定量摄取，应该能坚持到400天
which I figure I can stretch to 400 if I ration.
所以，我得想办法
So I got to figure out a way to grow
在这个不毛之地上
three years' worth of food here.
给自己种出三年的口粮来
On a planet where nothing grows.
幸运的是
Luckily...
我是个植物学家
I'm a botanist.
火星，你等着瞧吧你
Mars will come to fear my botany powers.
(STRAINING)
舱压已稳定
FEMALE AUTOMATED VOICE: Pressure stable.
缝合钉跑出来了
Staple came out.
第24个太阳日
(PANTING)
操你大爷的，小火星
Fuck you, Mars.
第31个太阳日
臭死了，约翰森
Johanssen, Jesus.
(GAGS)
第36个太阳日
周日, 周一，开心日
MEN: Sunday, Monday, Happy Days
周二, 周三，开心日
Tuesday, Wednesday, Happy Days
周四, 周五，开心日
Thursday, Friday, Happy Days
周末到了，摩托车响了
The weekend comes, my cycle hums
准备奔你而去
Ready to race to you
水源是个大问题
WATNEY: The problem is water.
我开辟了126平方米的土地
I have created 126 square meters of soil.
但是每立方米土壤
But every cubic meter of soil requires
需要40公升水才能让植物存活
40 liters of water to be farmable.
所以我需要更多的水
So I gotta make a lot more water.
幸好，我知道造水的秘诀
Good thing is, I know the recipe.
氢气和氧气燃烧生成水
You take hydrogen, you add oxygen, you burn.
现在，我可以从飞行器那儿
Now, I have hundreds of liters
搞到几百公升的联氨（N2H4，火箭燃料）
of unused hydrazine at the MDV.
在铱催化剂作用下
If I run the hydrazine over an iridium catalyst,
它能分解成氮气和氢气
it'll separate into N2 and H2.
然后将氢气引到一个特定区域
And then if I just direct the hydrogen into a small area...
点火燃烧即可
and burn it.
值得庆幸的是，在人类历史上
Luckily, in the history of humanity...
用火燃烧氢气
nothing bad has ever happened
从没发生什么坏事儿
from lighting hydrogen on fire.
航天局那些人不喜欢火
NASA hates fire.
因为他们总说
Because of the whole
“太空里玩火会引火烧身”
"fire makes everybody die in space" thing.
所以，他们给我们用的一切东西
So, everything they sent us up here with
都是阻燃材料做的
is flame-retardant...
当然，我所说的不包括
with the notable exception of...
马丁内兹的私人物品
Martinez's personal items.
抱歉了，马丁内兹
I am sorry, Martinez.
如果你不想让我乱翻你的东西
But if you didn't want me to go through your stuff...
你就不该把我丢在这儿等死
you shouldn't have left me for dead on a desolate planet.
我想，鉴于我的这种情况
By the way, I'm figuring you're gonna be
你应该不会生气的
fine with this, given my present situation.
THE FONZ ON TV: What's everybody doing?
Taking a holiday from being cool?
靠你了
Counting on you.
(BLOWING)
(SIZZLING)
哇哦！
Whoo!
(GROANS)
(EARS RINGING)
是的，没错，我把自己炸飞了
So, yeah, I blew myself up.
很有可能是因为…
Best guess...
我在计算的时候忘记了…
I forgot to account for the excess oxygen...
把自己呼出的氧气算进去了
that I've been exhaling when I did my calculations.
我真是蠢到家了
Because I'm stupid.
我等会儿再回去工作
Yeah, I'm gonna get back to work here...
现在我的耳朵叫个不停
just as soon as my ears stop ringing.
一个有趣的事情是
Interesting side note,
喷气推进实验室也是这么成立的
this is actually how the Jet Propulsion Lab was founded.
加州理工学院的五个家伙想制造火箭燃料
Five guys at Caltech were trying to make rocket fuel...
还差点把自己的宿舍烧了
and they nearly burned down their dorm.
学校不但没有开除他们
And rather than expel them...
反倒把他们赶去附近的一个农场
they banished them to a nearby farm,
叫他们继续完成实验
told them to keep working.
这样，我们才有了今天的太空计划
And now we have a space program.
(GASPS)
好了
Okay.
(SNORING)
第48个太阳日
第54个太阳日
你好啊，小家伙
Hey, there.
这个国家感到十分荣幸
SANDERS: The nation was blessed
能有像马克这样的人才参与太空计划
to have Mark serving in our space program.
在深感悲痛的同时
While his loss will be deeply felt...
航天局的所有工作人员
the men and women of NASA will soldier forth...
依然致力于推进航天事业的发展
onward and upward in the mission of their agency.
泰迪·桑德斯
航天局局长
他们有幸可以接替
By doing so, they honor the legacy
马克未完成的事业
Mark's leaving behind...
并保证马克的牺牲没有白费
and they ensure his sacrifice will not be in vain.
约翰逊太空中心
休斯顿，德克萨斯州
文森特·卡普尔
火星任务负责人
我很荣幸的说
I have the honor of speaking
不仅是NASA的职员
not only for the men and women of NASA...
并且也是全世界的人们...
but for people all over the world...
你的演讲很不错
VINCENT: I thought you gave a lovely speech, by the way.
(TURNS OFF TV)
我需要你批准我使用卫星
I need you to authorize my satellite time.
那是不可能的
It's not gonna happen.
国会资助了我们五次战神任务
We're funded for five Ares missions.
我相信我可以说服国会再批准一次
I think I can get Congress to authorize a sixth.
不行
No.
战神3任务只完成了18天
Ares 3 evac'd after 18 sols.
火星上还剩一半的物资储备
There's half a mission worth of supplies up there.
我此次的计划
I can sell it at a fraction
只需要使用一小部分资金
of the cost of a normal mission...
所以我想知道火星上还剩下些什么
and all I have to know is what's left of our assets.
不只是你一个人需要用卫星
You're not the only one who needs satellite time.
战神4任务的补给计划就要开始了
We've got the Ares 4 supply missions coming up.
我们的任务重点是夏帕雷利环形山
We should be focusing on the Schiaparelli Crater.
上面有12个卫星
Okay, we got 12 satellites up there.
我相信我可以使用几个小时…
Surely we can spare a few hours...
我说的不是这个问题，文斯
It's not about the satellite time, Vince.
我们是一个公开领域的组织
We're a public domain organization.
所有行动都要公开透明
We need to be transparent on this.
这我明白
Okay.
一旦卫星指向居住舱
The second we point the satellites at the Hab...
我们就相当于把
I broadcast pictures
马克·沃特尼的尸体照片发给世界各地了
of Mark Watney's dead body to the world.
你是害怕舆论的压力吗？
You're afraid of a PR problem?
我当然害怕舆论压力
Of course I'm afraid of a PR problem.
还说其他任务？
Another mission?
如果尸体的照片上了华盛顿邮报头条
Congress won't reimburse us for a paper clip...
国会连一个子儿
if I put a dead astronaut on the front page
也不会拨给我们
of The Washington Post.
他会一直在那里的，泰迪
He's not going anywhere, Teddy. I mean, he's not...
他的尸体不会分解腐烂的
He's not gonna decompose, you know.
他会永远在那里
He's gonna be up there forever.
不出意外的话，气象预测在未来的一年里
Meteorology estimates that he'll be covered in sand...
他会被风沙掩埋
from normal weather activity within a year.
我们等不了一年，还有工作要做
We can't wait a year. We got work to do.
战神5号五年以后才会发射
Ares 5 won't even launch for five years.
我们时间多的是
We have plenty of time.
好的
Okay.
好吧
这样，设想一下
Okay, consider this. (CLEARS THROAT)
现在，整个世界是站在我们这边的
Right now, the world's on our side.
大家都很同情沃特尼的家人
Sympathy for the Watney family.
战神6号可以把他的遗体带回来
Ares 6 could bring his body home.
当然，这并不是任务的目的
Now, we don't say that's the purpose of the mission...
但我们可以明确说，这是任务的其中一个计划
but we make it clear that that would be a part of it.
我们就这样跟外界说
We frame it that way.
这样我们就能得到国会的支持，当然前提是不能等一年
More support from Congress. But not if we wait a year.
一年以后，谁他妈还在乎这件事
We wait a year, nobody gives a shit.
(MICROWAVE TIMER DINGS)
(INDISTINCT RADIO CHATTER)
航天局指挥中心
约翰逊太空中心，休斯顿，德克萨斯州
凌晨1点30分
(COMPUTER CHIMES)
明迪·帕克
航天局卫星通讯员
文森特·卡普尔？
Vincent Kapoor?
6-2
6-2.
7-6-2
7-6-2.
阿西达利亚平原
Acidalia Planitia.
什么？
What?
安保吗？
Hi. Security?
我是卫星通讯员明迪·帕克
This is Mindy Park in SatCon.
紧急情况，我需要联系文森特·卡普尔
I need the emergency contact for Vincent Kapoor.
没错，是他
Yes, him.
没错，是紧急情况！
Yes, it's an emergency!
凌晨2点30分
确定吗？
SANDERS: How sure?
百分之百确定
100%.
开什么玩笑呢
You've got to be shitting me.
安妮·蒙特罗斯
航天局媒体公关主管
证明给我看
SANDERS: Prove it to me.
首先
For a start...
太阳能电池板变干净了
the solar panels have been cleaned.
也有可能是风吹干净的
They could have been cleaned by wind.
退回去，看2号探测车
Back it up. Look at Rover 2.
根据日志记录
According to the logs,
刘易斯队长在第17个太阳日
Commander Lewis took it out on Sol 17...
开到居住舱充电
plugged it into the Hab to recharge.
车子位置变化了
It's been moved.
她有可能忘记记录位置变化了
She could have forgotten to log the move.
不太可能
No, not likely.
为什么不直接问刘易斯呢？
ANNIE: Why don't we just ask Lewis?
我们联系通讯员，直接问清楚
Let's get on CAPCOM and ask her directly right now.
不，不行
SANDERS: No. No.
如果沃特尼还活着
If Watney is really alive,
我们决不能让他的队友们知道
we don't want the Ares 3 crew to know.
你怎么能把他们蒙在鼓里？
How can you not tell them?
他们还要10个月才能返回地球
They have another 10 months on their trip home.
太空航行危险重重
Space travel is dangerous.
他们必须保持警惕，不能受任何事情干扰
They need to be alert and undistracted.
可是他们认为马克已经死了
But they already think he's dead.
如果他们知道马克被他们抛弃了
And they'd be devastated to find out
他们肯定更加痛不欲生
they left him there alive.
你们没有想清楚
ANNIE: I'm sorry, but you have not thought this through.
我们要怎么对外界说
What are we gonna say? "Dear America...
“亲爱的民众，还记得那个已经死去”
"remember that astronaut we killed
“并风光下葬的宇航员吗？”
"and had a really nice funeral for?
“没想到他还活着，被我们抛弃在火星上了，真是不好意思”
"Turns out he's alive and we left him on Mars. Our bad.
“诚挚问候你们，航天局敬上”
"Sincerely, NASA."
你知道我们要经受多少舆论攻击吗？
Do you realize the shitstorm that is about to hit us?
我们要怎么向公众交代？
How are we going to handle the public?
按理说，24小时内我们必须得发布这些照片
Legally, we have 24 hours to release these pictures.
发布照片时附上说明
We release a statement with them.
我们不能让民众瞎猜
We don't want people working it out on their own.
是，局长
Yes, sir.
但如果我没算错的话，在我们能帮到他前
But if my math is right, he's going to starve to death
他早就饿死了
long before we can help him.
不敢想象他在火星得多难熬
Can you imagine what he's going through up there?
距离地球5千万公里
He's 50 million miles away from home.
独自一人
He thinks he's totally alone.
他认为我们抛弃了他
He thinks we gave up on him.
这对他的心理该是多大的摧残？
What does that do to a man, psychologically?
他此时此刻在想什么？
What the hell is he thinking right now?
(DISCO MUSIC PLAYING)
如果我再继续听下去
I'm definitely gonna die up here...
绝对会被这烂掉渣的迪斯科音乐折磨死
if I have to listen to any more god-awful disco music.
天啊，刘易斯队长
My God, Commander Lewis,
你带来的音乐简直是老掉牙了
couldn't you have packed anything from this century?
跟着旋律起舞
WOMAN: Turn the beat around
不，我才不要跟着旋律起舞
No, lam not gonna "turn the beat around."
我拒绝
I refuse to. (MUSIC STOPS)
桑德斯局长？桑德斯局长？
(REPORTERS CLAMORING) Mr. Sanders? Mr. Sanders?
为了联系马克·沃特尼
What attempts have been made
你们做了哪些努力？
to make contact with Mark Watney?
我们还在继续努力中
We're working on it.
他有足够的补给存活下去吗？
Does he have enough supplies to survive?
我们会尽快调查的
We'll be looking into that.
这对航天局有什么影响？
What does this say about the agency?
你会辞职吗？
Are you gonna resign?
不会
No.
桑德斯局长！
Director Sanders!
第70个太阳日
是时候做长远打算了
WATNEY: It's time to start thinking long term.
下次航天局的任务是战神4号
The next NASA mission is Ares 4...
降落地点是夏帕雷利环形山
and it's supposed to land at Schiaparelli Crater...
在3200公里之外
3200 kilometers away.
3200公里
3,200 kilometers.
四年之后，战神4号的队员抵达时
In four years, when the next Ares crew arrives,
我得在那儿
I'll have to be there.
也就是我要向环形山进发
Which means I have to get to the crater.
现在，问题是
Okay, so here's the rub.
现在只有一台探测车可以工作
I've got one working Rover
它的最大里程是35公里
designed to go a max distance of 35 kilometers...
之后就需要回到居住舱充电
before the battery has to be recharged at the Hab.
这只是问题A
That's Problem A.
问题B是这段路我得花
Problem B is this journey's gonna take me
差不多50天才能走完
roughly 50 days to complete.
所以我要在一个探测车里生活50天
So I gotta live for 50 days...
携带一个只有面包车大小的
inside a Rover with marginal life support
生命补给系统
the size of a small van.
在这种压倒性的劣势下
So, in the face of overwhelming odds,
我只有一个办法
I'm left with only one option.
那就是“实践出真知”
I'm gonna have to science the shit out of this.
差点睡着了
I almost went down.
Man.
好的，目前来说还算成功
Okay, so, success.
呃...
Uh...
从1号探测车卸下来的电池让电量增加了一倍
I have doubled my battery life by scavenging Rover 1.
但是如果打开加热器
But if I use the heater...
每天都要耗费一半的电量
I will burn through half my battery every day.
如果我不用加热器，我就会…
If I do not use my heater, I will be...
因为热力学定律而慢性死亡
(LAUGHS) slowly killed by the laws of thermodynamics.
我现在很乐意解决这个问题，但是…
I would love to solve this problem right now but unfortunately...
我的蛋蛋都冻僵了
my balls are frozen.
不行了，不行了，今天到此为止
I can't. I'm calling it. I'm calling it.
好消息就是，我有办法
Good news, I may have a solution
解决加热器的问题了
to my heating problem.
坏消息就是，我得把
Bad news, it involves me digging up
放射性同位素温差发电器挖出来
the Radioisotope Thermoelectric Generator.
如果我没记错的话
Now, if I remember my training correctly,
我曾被告知
one of the lessons was titled...
“不要把那个放射性的玩意儿挖出来，马克”
"Don't Dig Up the Big Box of Plutonium, Mark."
我知道，这种发电机很适用于航天器
I get it. RTGs are good for spacecraft,
但是如果它产生破裂
but if they rupture around humans...
所有人都会死翘翘
no more humans.
所以来到火星之后我们就把它埋了
Which is why we buried it when we arrived.
并在旁边插了个旗子
And planted that flag...
这样我们就不会
so we would never be stupid enough
再回到这个地方
to accidentally go near it again.
但是只要它完好无缺就没事
But as long as I don't break it...
我差点就欢呼雀跃地喊出
I almost just said
“一切都会好起来”
"Everything will be fine" out loud.
重要的是，我一点儿也不冷了
Look, the point is, I'm not cold anymore.
当然，我也可以承认
And sure, I could choose to think
我不冷的原因是
about the fact that I'm warm...
我身后有个核衰减的
because I have a decaying
放射性同位素发电机
radioactive isotope riding right behind me...
但是，我现在有个更棘手的问题
but right now, I got bigger problems on my hands.
那就是我搜索了刘易斯队长
I have scoured every single data file
硬盘上的每个文件
on Commander Lewis' personal drive.
这首是听起来最不像迪斯科舞曲的一首歌了
This is officially the least disco song she owns.
我渴望有个热情的男人
WOMAN: Lookin' for some hot stuff
BMG: 唐娜·桑默－火热尤物
BMG: Donna Summer－Hot Stuff
...宝贝, 今夜...
Baby, this evenin'
今夜需要有个热情的男人,宝贝
I need some hot stuff, baby, tonight
今夜我渴望有个热情的男人, 宝贝
I want some hot stuff, baby, this evenin'
该要有个热情的男人， 今晚需要一些快活
Gotta have some hot stuff Gotta have some love tonight
热情的男人
Hot stuff
我需要热情的男人
I need hot stuff
我渴望有个热情的男人
I want some hot stuff
我需要热情的男人
I need hot stuff
沃特尼要去哪里？
Yeah. Where is Watney going?
我们认为他在为一次远行做准备
We believe that he's preparing for a journey.
他测试的次数不断增加
He's been conducting incremental tests...
2号探测车每次开出去的时间
taking the Rover 2 out for longer
也越来越长
and longer trips each time.
(REPORTERS CLAMORING)
他要去哪儿？他为什么要离开
To what end? Why would he leave
相对安全的居住舱？
the relative safety of the Hab?
我们推测他计划要去战神4号的发射地点
Well, we think that he plans to travel to the Ares 4 launch site...
这样就可以联系上我们
in order to make contact with us,
但此举也十分危险
but it would be a dangerous gamble.
如果我们能联系上他
But if we could talk to him,
我们会让他待在居住舱
we would tell him to stay put...
并告诉他，我们正在竭尽所能
and to trust that we are doing everything in our power
让他毫发无损地回到地球
to bring him home alive.
谢谢大家
Thank you very much.
(REPORTERS CLAMORING)
你刚才问我怎么做的，我现在给你我的回答
You asked me how you did, and I'm giving you my answer.
我的回答是...
My answer is...
嗯...
Uh...
我本来想让人们忘了...
Look, I'm gonna make people forget...
马克·沃特尼有很大的可能性会挂掉...
there's a very strong possibility that Mark Watney could die...
因为这是你们付钱让我干这个
because that is what you are paying me for.
不幸的是，我需要这份工作
And unfortunately, I need this job...
因为我现在要给两个游手好闲的前夫付生活费
because currently I am paying alimony to two deadbeat ex-husbands...
因为某种程度上，性别平等害死我了
because somehow, gender equality has bitten me square in the ass.
很难相信
Hard to believe.
我甩了他们
I left them.
不要说能让他毫发无损地回来
And don't say "Bring him home alive."
这提醒了整个世界他可能会死
It reminds the world he might die.
不要说能让他毫发无损地回来，文森特
Don't say "Bring him home alive," Vincent.
这些访谈并非易事
You know what? These interviews aren't easy.
我说一些积极向上的话又能怎样
So God forbid I try to say something proactive and positive.
安妮
SANDERS: Annie.
不要再让文森特接受采访，明白了
No more Vincent on TV. Copy that.
76公里，这是真的吗？
76 kilometers. Am I reading that right?
你在问我吗？
MINDY: Are you asking me?
是的
SANDERS: l am.
没错
Yes, sir.
马克从居住舱出发，直行两小时
Mark drove two hours straight away from the Hab...
出舱活动后又开了两个小时
did a short EVA and then drove for another two.
他出舱活动应该是为了换电池
We think the EVA was to change batteries.
他没有带上氧合器
He didn't load up the oxygenator
或者水回收器吗？
or the water reclaimer?
每隔41小时，我们就会有17分钟的盲区时间
Every 41 hours, there's a 17 minute gap.
由于卫星轨道的工作方式
It's just the way the orbits work...
所以，我们可能会错过一些事情
so it's possible that we missed something.
把盲区时间降到4分钟
I want that gap down to four minutes.
我现在把调整轨道
I'm giving you total authority
和卫星轨迹的授权给你
over satellite trajectories and orbital adjustments.
别让我失望
Make it happen.
好的
Okay.
我们假设帕克小姐没有遗漏任何事情
Let's assume Miss Park didn't miss anything.
也就是说，马克目前还没到达战神4号任务地点
So Mark's not going to Ares 4. Yet.
当然，他也知道这是
But he's smart enough to figure out
他活下去的唯一希望
that's his only chance.
布鲁斯，补给最早什么时候可以送到火星？
Bruce, what's the earliest we can get a pre-supply there?
鉴于目前地球和火星的相对位置
With the positions of Earth and Mars,
布鲁斯·吴
喷气推进实验室主任
一共需要9个月
it'll take nine months.
设备的建造就要花费6个月
It'll take six months to build it in the first place.
我给你3个月
Three months.
3个月？
Three?
我知道你会说不可能
SANDERS: You're going to say it's impossible
然后我就会做个发言
and then I'm gonna make a speech...
夸奖你们实验室丰功伟绩
about the blinding capabilities
没有做不到的事情
of the JPL team...
然后你想想之后
and then you're going to do the math
就会对我说
in your head and say something like...
“加班加点工作是个噩梦”之类的话
"The overtime alone will be a nightmare."
加班加点工作本来就是个噩梦
The overtime alone will be a nightmare.
快开始吧
SANDERS: Get started.
我来筹集资金
I'll find you the money.
我们得告诉他们
We need to tell the crew.
米奇·亨德森
赫尔墨斯号飞行指挥官
米奇，这个我们讨论过了
VINCENT: Mitch, we've discussed this.
不，是你自己擅自决定的
No, you discussed this.
我才是那个小组的负责人
I'm the one who decides what's best for the crew.
他们有权知道
They deserve to know.
等救援计划落实了，我们自然会告诉他们
Once there's a real rescue plan, we'll tell them.
现在说没有任何意义
Otherwise, it's moot.
布鲁斯有3个月时间来做准备工作
Bruce has three months to get the payload done.
这是目前最重要的问题
That's all that matters right now.
我们会尽力的
We'll do our best.
马克的命运就在你们手上了
Mark dies if you don't.
第79个太阳日
距离我种下土豆已经过去48个太阳日了
WATNEY: It's been 48 sols since I planted the potatoes.
是时候收获果实，重新播种了
So now it's time to reap and re-sow.
它们比预期长得还好
They grew even better than I expected.
现在，我有400棵土豆
I now have 400 healthy potato plants.
我把土豆挖出来，并保持植株成活
I dug them up, being careful to leave their plants alive.
小颗的重新种下去
The smaller ones I'll reseed,
大颗的作为食品供应
the larger ones are my food supply.
纯天然，有机的火星土豆
All natural, organic, Martian-grown potatoes.
这种事情不太常见，对吧？
You don't hear that every day, do you?
当然，如果联系不上航天局
And by the way, none of this matters at all...
种再多的土豆也无济于事
if I can't figure out a way to make contact with NASA.
我有办法了
I know what I'm gonna do.
他又行动了
Oh! He's moving again.
他到底是要去哪？
Where the hell is he going?
他已经连续13天没改变方向了
He hasn't changed course for 13 days.
行驶方向也不是朝着战神4号
He's nowhere near the Ares 4.
或许他走了一些弯路
Unless he's not taking a direct route.
比如想避开一些障碍什么的
He might be trying to avoid some obstacle.
哪有什么障碍？
What obstacle?
那里是阿西达利亚平原
It's Acidalia Planitia.
那里什么都没有，除了…
There's nothing out there except the...
除了什么？
What?
我需要找一张地图
I need a map.
这个
Yeah.
伙计，你在干什么？
Hey, come on. What are you doing?
没事，没事
It's all right. It's all right.
我能借下这个吗？
Can I borrow this?
好，他的居住舱在哪里？
Okay, so where is the Hab location?
北纬31.2°，西经28.5°
31.2 degrees north, 28.5 degrees west.
好的
Okay. Mmm-hmm.
沃特尼现在在哪里？
Where's Watney? Uh...
这儿
There.
好的
VINCENT: Okay.
我知道他要去哪儿了
Okay. I know where he's going.
我得去赶飞机了
I need to get on an airplane.
(PANTING)
喷气推进实验室
帕萨迪纳，加利福尼亚州
文森特，你好
Vincent, how are you?
很高兴见到你
Good to see you.
飞行还顺利吗？
Good flight? Uh...
还行
Yeah.
它就放在那个角落的仓库里
It's in storage just around the corner.
文森特，很高兴再次见到你
Hey, Vincent, nice to see you again.
很高兴见到你
Nice to see you.
马克能让它恢复工作的几率有多大？
What are the chances Mark can get it working again?
不好说，97年就和它失去联系了
It's hard to say. We lost contact in '97.
我们认为可能是电池失效了
We think it was battery failure.
不过我还是想说一下
Though I'd like to point out
它的工作时长比预期超出3倍…
it lasted three times longer than expected in any...
布鲁斯，别担心，没人批评你们的工作
Nobody's criticizing JPL's work, Bruce.
我只是想和97年的工作人员
I just need to speak to everybody
见一面
that was here in '97.
他们都在这儿了，各位
They're already here. Guys.
我给你们介绍一下，这是文森特·卡普尔
I'd like to introduce Vincent Kapoor.
航天局火星任务负责人
Director of Mars Missions for NASA.
这是我们现在的团队
This is our current team...
他们是原来的团队成员
and our original project members.
- 这是复制品吗？- 没错
Is this the replica? TECHNICIAN: This is her.
好的，打开看看吧
Okay. Let's see it.
探路者号
Pathfinder.
第109个太阳日
(WHIRRING)
加油，加油
Come on. Come on.
(INDISTINCT CONVERSATIONS)
(BEEPING)
靠，有反应了
Holy shit. Okay.
“广播状态”
"Broadcasting status.
“监听遥测信号”
"Listening for telemetry signal."
然后呢？
Uh-huh.
好的，信号捕获成功
TIM: Okay. Signal acquired.
(VINCENT LAUGHING)
(CLAPS HANDS)
太好了  - 好的
VINCENT: All right. TIM: Okay.
摄像头准备
Camera.
好了，拍一张全景照.
Okay, taking panoramic image now.
收到信号没？好
You receiving yet? Yeah.
我正在想，我们看见一个生机勃勃的红色行星还不如
I just thought we'd all rather look at a black screen...
看一个纯黑的屏幕.
instead of a vibrant red planet.
怎么了？
Excuse me?
帝姆是我们最好的通讯专家
Tim's our finest comm tech.
我们很欣赏他的刻薄
We all appreciate his acerbic wit.
严肃点行么？
I will kill you.
(BEEPING)
数据传过来了.
Incoming.
“能收到吗？”
"Are you receiving me?"
“能，不能”
"Yes. No."
(CHUCKLES)
把摄像头对准“能”
Okay, point the camera at "yes."
来回通讯时间需要32分钟
32-minute round-trip communications time.
他只能问我们能或不能的问题
All he can do is ask yes or no questions...
而我们只能旋转摄像头
and all we can do is point the camera.
这个会议真是开的“既有效”
This won't exactly be an Algonquin Round Table
“又不无聊”啊
of snappy repartee.
你说什么？ - 蒂姆，蒂姆
Are you kidding me? Tim, Tim.
别废话，让摄像机转起来  - 收到
Just point the camera. TIM: Roger that.
转动摄像机
Pointing the camera.
哇哦！
Whoo!
太棒了！
Yes!
问题又来了
So here's the rub.
我们得想个办法
Somehow we have to have complex
用一台1996年的
astrophysical engineering conversations...
(MICROWAVE TIMER BEEPING)
静态画面照相机来讨论
using nothing but a still-frame camera...
天体物理学
from 1996.
幸运的是
Luckily...
照相机还是能转的
the camera does spin.
所以我可以做个字母表
So I can make an alphabet.
不能是现在用的字母表
It can't be our alphabet.
360°分给26个字母加一个问题板
26 characters plus a question card
字母板之间的间隙只有13°
into 360 gives us 13 degrees of arc.
太窄了
That's way too narrow.
根本分不清摄像头指的是哪个字母
I'd never know what the camera was pointing at.
喔.
Ooh.
用十六进制
Hexadecimals.
十六进制可以帮上大忙
Hexadecimals to the rescue.
我猜想你们其中一个
I figured one of you guys
应该会有ASCII信息交换码
kept an ASCII table lying around.
果真没错
And I was right.
女士们，先生们
Ladies and gentlemen,
隆重介绍超级书呆子，贝丝·约翰森
I give you super-nerd Beth Johanssen.
她的手提电脑里还有“魔域2”
Who also had copies of Zork ll...
和“福波斯的皮衣女神”游戏
and Leather Goddesses of Phobos on her personal laptop.
(LAUGHING)
约翰森，你太逗了
Seriously, Johanssen...
在这里比待在空无一人的博物馆还孤独
it's like the Smithsonian of loneliness on there.
我不是在抱怨什么，太棒了！
Not that I'm complaining. Yes!
我对孤独又了解多少呢？
Who am I to talk about loneliness?
我知道他想做什么
I know where he's going with this.
(MOANS SOFTLY)
F，O
"F, O-u
7，W
“7, will
你还好吗？
(BEEPING)
文森特
Vincent.
文森特，醒醒
Vincent, wake up.
(GROANS)
我现在很好
肚子被天线刺了个洞
生命监测仪也坏了
队员以为我死了
不是他们的错
因为现在可以进行更加复杂的对话
Now that we can have more complicated conversations...
航天局的智囊团给我出了个主意
the smart people at NASA have sent me instructions
他们教我侵入探测车的电脑
on how to hack the Rover...
让它能和探路者通讯
so that it can talk to Pathfinder.
我只需要篡改一小部分代码
If I hack a tiny bit of code.
也就是操作系统的20个指令
just 20 instructions in the Rover's operating system...
航天局就可以将探测车连接到
NASA can link the Rover to Pathfinder's
探路者的广播频率
broadcasting frequency...
一切就大功告成了
and we're in business.
马克
"Mark...
我是文森特·卡普尔
"this is Vincent Kapoor.
我们从第54个太阳日开始关注你
"We've been watching you since Sol 54.
整个世界都为你加油
"The whole world is rooting for you.
能想到用探路者号来联络，真的很了不起
"Amazing job getting Pathfinder.
我们正在研究救援计划
"We're working on rescue plans.
与此同时，我们也在准备物资补给
"Meantime, we're putting together a supply mission...
让你能坚持到战神4号的到来
"to keep you fed until Ares 4 arrives."
好的
Okay.
(BEEPING)
有消息了
Okay.
很高兴收到你们的消息，终于不用等死了
"Glad to hear it. Really looking forward to not dying."
(ALL LAUGHING)
(APPLAUSE) (PEOPLE WHOOPING)
队员们怎么样？
"How's the crew?"
知道我还活着，他们说了什么？
"What did they say when they found out I was alive?"
收到了吗？马克
各位，能让我们单独待一会儿吗？
Guys, can we get some space please?
我也要走？
Me?
没错
Yeah, you.
给我点时间
Give me a sec.
告诉他吧
Just tell him.
我们还没有告诉他们你还活着
"We haven't told the crew you are alive yet.
他们还有任务，不能分心
"We need them to concentrate on their mission."
(EXHALES)
妈的说什么？！
What the fuck?
我去你妈的！
他说，“他们不知道我还活着？”
Okay, he says, "They don't know I'm alive?
“去你妈的”
"What the..." F-word.
还有更多的“去你妈的”
F-word in gerund form.
“你他妈的有什么毛病？”
F-word, again, what's wrong with you?"
(ALL LAUGHING)
马克，请注意你的用词
"Mark, please watch your language.
你说的每一句话
"Everything you type
都在进行世界直播
"is being broadcast live all over the world."
是吗？
Yeah?
(ALL GASPING)
我的天哪
VINCENT: Oh, my God.
(SIGHS)
什么是felcher？
What's a felcher?
是的，先生. 他现在承受着巨大压力
SANDERS: Yes, sir. He is under a tremendous amount of stress.
我明白，我们正在处理
I understand. We're working on it.
谢谢您，总统先生
Thank you, Mr. President.
我刚才跟总统解释过
I just had to explain to the President of the United States...
什么叫官僚主义Felcher.
what a beaurocratic felcher is.
我犯贱去Google了一下
I made the mistake of typing it into Google.
别介意
Don't.
马克是对的
Problem is, Mark's right.
这么拖下去，事情会更糟
The longer we wait, the worse it's gonna get.
我们得告诉他们
We need to tell the crew.
文森特不在的时候，你提出这个事情
You're bringing this up while Vincent is in Pasadena...
这样他就没法反驳你了
so he can't argue the other side.
我根本不用管文森特的意见
I shouldn't have to answer to Vincent.
或者其他任何人的意见
Or anyone else.
该告诉他们了，泰迪
It's time, Teddy.
赫尔墨斯号
离开火星4个月后
(BEEPING)
刘易斯队长？
JOHANSSEN: Commander Lewis?
说吧
Go ahead.
数据转存基本完成了
JOHANSSEN: Data dump is almost complete.
收到了，这就来
Copy that. On my way.
你挺着急的
You're in a hurry.
是啊
MARTINEZ: Yeah.
我儿子昨天3岁生日
My son turned three yesterday.
应该会有派对的照片传过来
Should be pictures of the party.
有一批私人信件
JOHANSSEN: Got a batch of personals.
我直接分发到你们的电脑里了
Dispatching them to your laptops now.
我就不用读沃格尔的德语恋物癖邮件了
I don't need to read Vogel's weird German fetish emails.
那些只是遥测更新数据
VOGEL: They're telemetry updates.
只要你感兴趣就行
Hey, whatever does it for you, man.
这里有一个视频消息
There's a video message.
是发给整个团队的
It's addressed to the whole crew.
打开吧，你们都过来
LEWIS: Play it. Come on, guys.
我也想加入你的恋物癖小组
BECK: I wanna get in on that telemetry action.
(MEN LAUGHING)
你们好，我是米奇，米奇·亨德森
Hi, hello. It's Mitch. Mitch Henderson.
我有些事情要说
I have some news.
只能通过这种方式告诉你们
There's no subtle way to put this.
马克·沃特尼还活着
Mark Watney is still alive.
我的天啊
Oh, my God. (ALL GASP)
我知道这令你们很诧异
I know that's a surprise and I know
我也知道你们肯定有很多问题
you will have a lot of questions.
以下是一些基本情况
But here are the basics.
马克还活着，也很健康
He's alive and he's healthy.
2个月前我们知道这个消息，并决定瞒着你们
We found out two months ago and decided not to tell you.
- 2个月前？- 我的天
Two months? Oh, my God.
我很反对航天局的做法
MITCH: I was strongly against that decision.
现在告诉你们是因为
We're telling you now because...
我们终于和他取得联系
we finally have communication with him...
并着手准备营救计划
and a viable rescue plan.
我们会发一份报告说明目前的情况
We'll give you a write-up of what happened,
一切细节都包括在内
a full write-up of everything.
但是这不是你们的错
But it's not your fault.
马克每次也都会强调这点
Mark stresses that every time it comes up.
所以…
So... Yeah...
你们花点时间来接受这个消息
Take some time to absorb this.
有什么问题尽管可以问
And send all the questions you want.
我们会一一解答
We'll answer them.
好吧，就这样
All right. Henderson out.
老天啊，他还活着
BECK: Holy shit, he's alive.
我抛弃了他
I left him behind.
不  - 不是
JOHANSSEN: No.  BECK: No.
我们都离开了
We all left together.
你们只是服从命令
You were following orders.
是我抛弃了他
I left him behind.
第128个太阳日
自从航天局和我取得联系后
WATNEY: So now that NASA can talk to me,
他们便一发不可收拾
they won't shut up.
他们想了解居住舱的实时变化
They want constant updates on every Hab system...
还有一屋子的人
and they got a room full of people
想要对我的农作物进行微观管理
trying to micromanage my crops.
这其实很酷
Which is awesome.
我虽然不想让你们觉得我很自大
Look, I don't mean to sound arrogant or anything...
但是我必须说，我是这个星球上最伟大的植物学家
but I am the greatest botanist on this planet, so...
还有个好处
One big bonus
自从联系上航天局后
to this communication with NASA again...
我又能收到邮件了
is the email. I'm getting them again.
就像以前在赫尔墨斯号上一样
Big data dumps like when I was on the Hermes.
我甚至还收到了总统的来信
I even got one from the president.
不过我收到的最拉风的一封信
The coolest one, though, the coolest one I got...
是芝加哥大学
was from University of Chicago,
我的母校寄来的
my alma mater.
他们说，一旦你在某个地方种了庄稼
They say that once you grow crops somewhere...
那个地方就是你的殖民地了
you've officially colonized it.
所以，可以这么说
So, technically...
我殖民了火星
I colonized Mars.
(ROCK THE BOAT PLAYING)
被打脸的滋味如何，尼尔·阿姆斯特朗  （第一个登月的人）
In your face, Neil Armstrong.
另一个消息就是
In other news, there's been a request...
他们希望我能摆拍一张照片
for me to pose for a photograph
下次联系时发回去
on my next transmission.
我正在琢磨拍照时
I'm trying to figure out whether
我应该走“学院风”
I should go with "High School Senior"...
还是“风骚派”
or "coquettish ingénue."
但是我不确定
But I'm not really sure
穿上宇航服拍还能不能这么美了
how that's gonna look with my spacesuit on.
(BEEPING)
嘿！
Hey!
他在干什么？
ANNIE: What is he doing?
我要的是正经照片，他这是在耍帅卖萌呢？
I asked for a photo, and what, he's The Fonz?
有照片给你就不错了，安妮
Just be grateful we got you something, Annie.
这个照片不能用，文森特，你知道的
I can't use this, Vincent, and you know that.
我想要一张他的正脸照
I need a picture of his face.
让他拿掉头盔照也不是不可以
I could tell him to take off his helmet...
但是，你知道的，他会死掉的
but then he'd, you know, die, so...
(ALL LAUGHING)
等救援行动的细节敲定之后
SANDERS: We'll release the photo
再发布这张照片
when we detail the rescue operation.
我准备宣布我们会在
I want to announce we're launching
明年的霍曼转移窗口
some supplies to him next year...
发送物资补给到火星
during the Hohmann Transfer Window.
布鲁斯，你们的工作在进度之内吧？
Bruce, your team's still on schedule?
虽然日程很紧，但是我们可以做到
It'll be tight, but we'll make it.
9个月的行程
Nine-month travel time.
我们的探测器在第868个太阳日才能到火星
That puts the probe to Mars on Sol 868.
植物学家那边的数据分析拿到了吗？
Did we get the botany team's analysis?
拿到了，他们估计马克的农作物可以让他坚持到第912个太阳日
Yeah, they estimate Mark's crops will last till Sol 912.
他们很不情愿地承认马克做得很出色
They grudgingly admit that he's doing great work.
很不情愿？
Grudgingly?
没错，因为只要他们
Yeah. Mark has a tendency to tell them
质疑马克的做法
to have sex with themselves...
马克就会对他们爆粗口
whenever they question one of his decisions.
让他注意点，文森特
SANDERS: Get him in line, Vincent.
这件事不能有任何偏差
We can't afford any miscommunication.
我讨厌事情没有余地
I hate this margin.
912天的食物，我们的补给第868天才能到
912 Sols worth of food. We get there on 868.
前提还是不能出任何差错
And that's assuming nothing goes wrong.
(ALARM BLARING) (AIR HISSING)
(SCREAMING)
(GROANING)
(GROANS)
检测到宇航服破裂
FEMALE AUTOMATED VOICE: Suit breach detected.
(PANTING)
氧气含量过低
Oxygen level critical.
氧气含量，10%
Oxygen level, 10%.
氧气含量，5%
Oxygen level, 5%.
宇航服压力已稳定
Suit pressure, stable.
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
(CONTINUES BREATHING HEAVILY)
舱压已稳定
FEMALE AUTOMATED VOICE: Pressure stable.
(BLOWING)
操！操！操！
God! God, God, God, God!
植物都死了
Crops are dead.
舱内失压导致植物水分汽化
Complete loss of pressure boiled off most of the water.
存活的细菌也因为
Any bacteria that survived,
暴露在火星极低温度下
died in the subzero temperatures...
而全部死亡
when exposed to Mars' atmosphere.
他还能撑多久？
ANNIE: How long does he have?
他还可以吃现有的土豆
(SIGHS) He can still eat the potatoes he has,
只是不能再种新的了
he just can't grow any more...
所以大概能坚持200个太阳日
so give him 200 sols.
居住舱的食物够他撑409个太阳日，对吗？
Rations get him to what? Sol 409?
没错，加上土豆的话，可以撑到第609天
Mmm-hmm. So with potatoes, 609.
所以到第868个太阳日，他早就死了
So by Sol 868, he'll be long dead.
我们得尽快发送补给
We're gonna have to launch as soon as possible...
行程时间也要进行调整
which changes our travel time.
我们正在努力
Yeah, we're working on it.
整个行程预估需要414天
Prelim estimates call for a 414-day trip.
现在是第135个太阳日
It's Sol 135 now.
安装助推器和例行检查
We need 13 days to mount the boosters,
需要13天
perform inspections...
也就是说，布鲁斯和他的团队
which gives Bruce and his team...
还有47天来准备探测器
47 days to make this probe.
去通知布鲁斯的差事，交给你了
I'll let you call Bruce, give him the news.
知道了
Okay.
我得去换件衣服
I'm gonna need a change of clothes.
第136个太阳日
亲爱的马克
MARTINEZ: "Dear Mark...
显然，航天局允许我们跟你联系了
"Apparently NASA's letting us talk to you now.
而我倒霉被抽中了
"And I drew the short straw.
(CHUCKLES)
很抱歉把你丢在了火星
"Sorry we left you behind on Mars.
那是因为你太讨人厌了
"But we just don't like you.
(ALL CHUCKLING)
还有，赫尔墨斯号没了你也更加宽敞了
"Also, it's a lot roomier on the Hermes without you.
虽然我们得轮流干你的活儿
"We have to take turns doing your tasks.
但植物学本来就是小菜一碟
"But, I mean, it's only botany.
(LAUGHING)
这都不算真正的科学
"it's not real science."
天啊
Oh, Jesus.
你在火星还好吗？
"How's Mars?"
亲爱的马丁内兹，我还好
WATNEY: "Dear Martinez, Mars is fine.
我不小心把居住舱给炸了
"I accidentally blew up the Hab...
但不幸的是
"but unfortunately,
路易斯队长的迪斯科舞曲一点事儿都没有
"all of Commander Lewis' disco music still survived."
但不幸的是
"But unfortunately,
路易斯队长的迪斯科舞曲一点事儿都没有
"all of Commander Lewis' disco music still survived."
每天，我都会去外面
WATNEY: "Every day, I go outside
看看一望无际的地平线
"and look at the vast horizons."
每天，我都会去外面
MARTINEZ: "Every day, I go outside
看看一望无际的地平线
"and look at the vast horizons."
提醒自己我还活着
WATNEY: "Just because I can."
MARTINEZ: "Just because I can.
代我向大家问好
"Tell the others I said hello."
没问题，伙计
"Will do, buddy."
(CHUCKLES SADLY)
(MACHINERY POWERING UP)
舱压已稳定
FEMALE AUTOMATED VOICE: Pressure stable.
(WIND HOWLING)
(PLASTIC RUSTLING)
5，10
5,10...
15，20，30，35
15, 20, 30, 35...
(SIGHS DEEPLY)
40.
52.
(GROANS LOUDLY)
喷气推进实验室
帕萨迪纳，加利福尼亚州
里奇
Rich.
醒醒
Wake up.
里奇·珀内尔
天体动力学家
抱歉，他们着急要探测器的航线
Sorry, but they're asking for the probe courses.
现在几点了？
What time is it?
凌晨3点42
It's 3:42.
(SPITS)
(CLATTERS)
我知道加班加点工作很辛苦
Look, I know we're coming at this backwards...
但是没有确切的数据
but we can't commit to a firm launch date
我们就不能确定探测器的发射日期
with this many unknowns.
没关系
It's all right. Um...
25个模拟航线都需要414天才能到火星
All 25 models for launch will take 414 days to reach Mars.
推力持续时间稍有不同
They vary slightly in thrust duration...
燃料要求也几乎相同
and the fuel requirement is nearly identical.
对发射来说不是个好时机，是吧？
Not a good time to launch, is it?
没错，地球和火星相对位置不太好
Yeah, Earth and Mars are really badly positioned.
想简单点儿你们还不如…
Heck, it'd almost be easier if you...
想简单点儿要怎样？
Almost easier to what?
我得再喝点咖啡
I need more coffee.
哎呀！
Ahh! (THUDS)
你没事吧？
MIKE: Are you all right?
没事
It's fine.
想简单点儿要怎样？
Almost easier to what?
你还知道我是你上司吧？
You do understand I'm your boss, right?
嗯哼
Uh-huh.
好吧，看一下这个两亿美元...
Okay, let's ask the $200 million...
对不起是5亿
I'm sorry 500...
这是5么？ 至少.
Is that a 5? At least.
好的，我们看看关键问题的进展如何
SANDERS: All right, let's ask the very, very expensive question.
探测器能按时交工吗？
Is the probe going to be ready on time?
- 我们的进度有些落后- 落后多少
BRUCE: We're behind.  Give me a number.
15天，再给我15天就能完成
15 days. 15 days and I can get it done.
可以，我们就再来创造15天时间
All right, let's create 15 days.
安装探测器需要13天
13 days to mount the probe.
能缩短吗？
Can we reduce?
其实只需要3天就可以完成安装
It actually only takes three days to mount the probe.
而且能缩短到2天，对吗？
And we can get that down to two, right?
可以缩短到2天
I can get it down to two.
测试和检查需要10天
10 days are for tests and inspections.
以前检查出问题的概率是多少？
How often do those inspections reveal a problem?
你的意思是省去检查这个环节吗？
Are you suggesting we don't do the inspections?
我只是在问检查出问题的概率是多少
Right now I'm asking how often they reveal a problem.
百分之五
One in 20.
但这只是发射前测出的理论值
But that's grounds for countdown halt.
我们不能冒这个险
MITCH: We can't take that chance.
还有什么好建议能争取点时间？
Anyone else know a safer way to buy more time?
凯勒医生，让沃特尼的食物多撑4天
Dr. Keller, stretch Watney's rations four more days.
虽然不是多好的主意，但是能凑足15天了
You're not gonna like it, but that'll get us to 15.
还有，省掉检查环节
And we'll cancel the inspections.
泰迪
Teddy.
- 如果这个消息传出去…- 我来负责
Sir, if that ever got out...    It's on me.
时间给你凑出来了
You got your two weeks.
抓紧完成
Get it done.
现在，我得坚持到
WATNEY: So, now I have to hold out
第154个太阳日
探测器送来食物的那天
until the probe gets here with more food.
想知道我每天摄入多少卡路里吗？
You want to see what minimal calorie count looks like?
标准配给
Standard issue ration.
但是现在不是一天吃3个
But instead of three of these every one day...
而是每3天吃一个
I'm now eating one of these every three days.
这个是烤肉卷
This is meatloaf.
这个是今天的食品配给
So, here's today's allotment...
当然，我已经补充了一个土豆
which, of course, I've supplemented with a potato...
我的怒火开始像一千个太阳的
which I'm beginning to hate with the fiery passion...
烈焰一样.
of 1,000 suns.
结果，他们现在又叫我
And now, they've asked me...
再少吃一点
to do that.
(DON'T LEAVE ME THIS WAY PLAYING)
关键是
The point is...
多省出4天的口粮
"stretch the rations four more days"...
真的是很让人蛋疼
(SIGHS) is a real dick-punch.
我准备用土豆蘸着止痛药吃
I'm gonna dip this potato in some crushed Vicodin.
反正没人能阻止我
And there's nobody who can stop me.
因为我的番茄酱7天前就吃完了
It has been seven days since I ran out of ketchup.
既然我们已经提前了发射计划....
And since we've pushed launch....
我们需要验证新的卫星参数
we need to account for the new satellite adjustments.
可我们连旧的卫星参数都没收到
We still haven't received the old satellite adjustments.
好吧，我两星期以前就跟你们说过了.
Well, I asked for those two weeks ago.
里奇在干什么？
What's Rich doing?
我们去他办公室的时候被吓回来了
We're scared to go in there.
里奇，你到底在干什么？
Rich, what the hell are you doing?
我需要你给我争取一点超级计算机的使用时间.
I need you to get me some supercomputer time.
你上次睡觉是什么时候？
When did you last sleep?
这很重要,麦克
It's important, Mike.
好吧，我试试看
All right, I'll do it.
好
Good.
喷气推进实验室，IRIS探测器
四周后
上升，再升一些
JPL TECHNICIAN 1: Up. Up, up. Yeah.
从这儿上去
Let's go up here.
标签朝上
JPL TECHNICIAN 2: Labels facing up.
卡纳维拉尔角
IRIS探测器发射台
我是飞行指挥官
This is the flight director.
开始发射前状态检查
Begin launch status check.
收到，指挥官，开始发射状态检查
Roger that, Flight. Beginning launch status check.
你信神吗，文森特？
Do you believe in God, Vincent?
相信
Yeah.
我父亲是印度教徒
Yeah, my father was a Hindu,
我母亲是基督教徒，所以我信
my mother is a Baptist, so, yeah".
而且我信好几种神
I believe in several.
希望神灵也可以保佑我们
We'll take all the help we can get.
发射状态检查完毕
LAUNCH CONTROL TECHNICIAN: Launch status check complete.
我是指挥官
MITCH: This is Flight.
准备发射
We are go for launch.
开始倒计时
TIMER CONTROLLER: Proceeding with the count.
10，9
10... 9...
8...
7， 6
7... 6...
主引擎启动
Main engines start.
4，3
4... 3...
2...
1.
发射
Liftoff.
推力良好
Good thrust.
各项性能指标正常
Performance is nominal.
轨迹显示一切正常
FEMALE TIMER: The tail is giving good data.
目前一切稳定，指挥官
TIMER CONTROLLER: She's rock solid at this point, Flight.
推进方向控制良好
TVCs look good.
(ALL CHEERING)
检测到异常震颤，指挥官
We're getting a little shimmy, Flight.
什么？
Say again?
目前已经出现较大偏差
We are getting a very large precession.
情况还好吗？
Are we good?
指挥官，出现安全警戒
TIMER CONTROLLER: Flight, it's hitting the redline.
绕长轴旋转，偏差达到17度
It's spinning on the long axis around a 17-degree precession.
发射台，什么情况？
Launch, what's happening?
探测器重力达到7个g
Force on Iris is 7 G's.
探测器参数已丢失，指挥官
COMMS TECHNICIAN: We've lost readings on the probe, Flight.
(ALL EXCLAIMING IN DISMAY)
我的天哪
Oh, Jesus Christ.
已经失去联系，指挥官
We've lost it, Flight.
卫星探测呢？
SatCon?
卫星无法捕获
SATCON TECHNICIAN: No satellite acquisition
探测器信号
of signal.
信号丢失
TIMER CONTROLLER: L.O.S.
L.O.S. here, too.
这里是美国驱逐舰斯托克顿号
CAPCOM TECHNICIAN: U. S. Destroyer Stockton
观测到有残骸从高空落下
reporting debris falling from the sky.
ICC各位员工
TIMER CONTROLLER: Everyone in the ICC,
保持在各自工作岗位
maintain your positions at your consoles.
地面控制中心，启动应急措施.
GC, lock the doors.
发射情况如何？沃特尼
第186个太阳日
刘易斯队长
WATNEY: "Commander Lewis...
我可能需要你为我做件事
"I may need you to do something for me.
如果我死了，希望你能去陪陪我父母
"If I die, I need you to check in on my parents.
他们应该想知道我们在火星的生活
"They'll wanna hear all about our time here on Mars.
我知道这是个苦差事
"I know that sucks.
我也知道谈论他们死去的儿子
"And it'll be hard talking to a couple...
会很痛苦
"about their dead son.
我知道这要求有点过分
"It's a lot to ask.
所以我只能找你
"Which is why I'm asking you.
我并没有放弃
"I'm not giving up.
我只是给自己做好各种打算
"We just need to prepare for every outcome.
请告诉他们
"Please tell them...
我爱我的工作
"Tell them I love what I do...
我也做的很出色
"and I'm really good at it.
我是为了
"And that I'm dying...
一个伟大…
"for something big...
壮丽…
"and beautiful...
高于个人的事业而牺牲的
"and greater than me.
告诉他们我能接受这样的结果
"Tell them I said I can live with that.
最后，告诉他们
"And tell them...
谢谢他们带我来到这个世界
"thank you for being my mom and dad."
中国国家航天局，北京
我们使用蛋白块
VINCENT: We substituted protein cubes
作为每天的食粮
for the standard rations.
发射时的推力
The thrust of the launch combined
加上同时的横向振动
with the simultaneous lateral vibration...
导致蛋白块液化，从而使负载失衡
liquefied the cubes and created an unbalanced load.
文森特，这种情况
Vincent, why wasn't this addressed
为什么检查环节时没有发现？
in the inspections phase?
因为为了能赶上发射期限
In order to make our launch window,
我们被迫加速了整个流程
we were forced to accelerate our schedule.
(BOTH SPEAKING MAN DARIN)
他们的宇航员将会饿死
Their astronaut is going to die.
郭明
中国航天局首席科学家
当然，还有其他的办法
Of course there are other ways...
朱涛
中国航天局副首席科学家
太阳神的助推器，我们的工程师检查过数据
...the Taiyang Shen booster. Our engineers have run the numbers,
它的容量可以到达火星的轨道
and it has enough fuel for a Mars injection orbit.
NASA为什么没有找我们？
Why hasn't NASA approached us?
因为他们不知道
They don't know.
我们的数据是绝密的
Our booster technology is classified.
也就是说，假如我们什么都不做
So if we do nothing...
世界将永远不会知道，其实，我们是可以帮的上忙的
The world would never know we could have helped.
那么，仅仅是为了论证，如果我们决定帮助他们
Then, for the sake of argument, let's say we decide to help them...
我们把助推器给了他们，也就是取消了太阳神计划
We'd be giving up a booster and effectively cancelling Taiyang Shen.
那我们就从航天的角度来解决问题，寻求合作
We need to keep this among scientists, a co-operation between space agencies.
是
SANDERS: Yes.
是的，我明白
Yes, I understand.
谢谢
Thank you.
太棒了！
Yes!
(SIGHS)
好了
BRUCE: All right.
感谢我的中国叔叔汤米
Thanks to my uncle Tommy in China,
我们还有一次机会
we get another chance at this.
上次，我们花62天完成了探测器
Now, we finished the Iris probe in 62 days.
这次，我们要在28天内完成
We are now gonna attempt to finish it in 28.
昴宿星团，航天局超级计算机
(CHIMES)
计算正确
我们可以抛弃着陆系统
We can jettison any kind of landing system.
只发送食物补给
We're only sending rations.
在火星实现摔机着陆
We can crash-land on Mars.
你应该把电话挂了
You should hang up the phone.
- 你是哪位？- 我是里奇·珀内尔
I'm sorry, who are you? My name is Rich Purnell.
我是天体动力学家
I work in Astrodynamics,
你现在应该把电话挂了
and you should hang up the phone right now.
好吧
All right, all right.
我回头打给你
I'm gonna call you back.
我知道怎么能救马克·沃特尼
I know how to save Mark Watney.
你们的探测器计划不可行，会出现很多差错
Your probe plan won't work. Too many things can go wrong.
我有更好的办法
I've got a better way.
你是天体动力学家？
Astrodynamics?
没错
Yeah.
“艾隆德计划”是个什么东西？
What the hell is "Project Elrond"?
我得给计划起个名字
VINCENT: I had to make something up.
但是“艾隆德”是什么意思？
But "Elrond"?
因为这是一个秘密会议
Because it's a secret meeting.
你怎么知道的？
How do you know that?
为什么“艾隆德”代表“秘密会议”？
Why does "Elrond" mean "secret meeting"?
艾隆德会议，出自指环王
The Council of Elrond. It's from Lord of the Rings.
指环王
Lord of the Rings.
在这个会议上他们决定毁掉那个魔戒
It's the meeting where they decide to destroy the One Ring.
如果要叫“艾隆德计划”的话
SANDERS: If we're gonna call something "Project Elrond"...
我希望我的代号叫“格洛芬德尔”
I would like my code name to be "Glorfindel."
我讨厌你们每一个人
Okay, I hate every one of you.
什么，连泰迪都不知道这个计划？
What, Teddy doesn't even know about this yet?
抱歉，你是谁？
I'm sorry, who are you?
他是里奇·珀内尔，天体动力学家
VINCENT: This is Rich Purnell, Astrodynamics.
把你刚才说的告诉他们
Tell them what you just told me.
我可以让赫尔墨斯号在第561个太阳日回到火星
I can get the Hermes back to Mars by Sol 561.
怎么做？
SANDERS: HOW?
麻烦你能站到那儿吗？
Could you stand right there for me, please?
谢谢
Thanks.
就是那儿，很好
Right there. Great.
你能站到那里吗，那里
And could you stand right there? Right there.
假设这个订书机是赫尔墨斯号
Okay, let's pretend that this stapler is the Hermes...
你是…
and you are...
抱歉，你叫什么来着？
I'm sorry, what's your name again?
泰迪，现任航天局局长
Teddy. I'm the Director of NASA.
酷，泰迪，你是地球
Cool. Teddy, you're Earth.
现在，赫尔墨斯号正驶向地球
And right now, the Hermes is headed towards you...
与此同时，开始减速，准备和地球对接
starting its month-long deceleration to intercept.
但是，我的建议是
But instead, what I'm proposing is...
(WHOOSHING)
现在就应该开始加速
we start accelerating immediately
从而达到更高的速度
to preserve velocity and gain even more.
我们不需要和地球对接
We don't intercept with Earth at all...
但是可以足够靠近地球
but we come close enough
来获得引力助推，并改变航向
to get a gravity assist and adjust course.
与此同时
While we're doing that...
我们用探测器实现食物补给
we resupply with the probe...
也就是太阳神
VINCENT: The Taiyang Shen.
带着任何要带的物资
...pick up whatever provisions we need...
加速飞向火星
and now we're accelerating towards Mars.
(WHOOSHING)
你是火星
You're Mars.
此时，因为速度太快无法进入火星轨道
Now, we're going too fast at this point to fall into orbit...
但是我们实现近飞对接
but we can do a flyby.
沃特尼又无法离开火星，实现近飞有什么用？
What good is a flyby if we can't get Watney off the surface?
沃特尼可以用飞行器实现对接
Watney would intercept using the MAV.
喔！
Ow!
(WHOOSHING)
然后就可以回家了
And then we just head home.
(WHOOSHING)
我计算过了，没有问题
I've done the math. It checks out.
里奇  - 先生
SANDERS: Rich.  Yes, sir.
滚出去
Get out.
好的
All right.
他是对的吗？ - 没错
Is he right?   VINCENT: Yeah.
布鲁斯，你怎么看？
SANDERS: Bruce, what do you think?
文森特说是对的那就没问题
Well, if Vincent says so.
这个计划要用到太阳神？
We need to use the Taiyang Shen?
没错
VINCENT: Uh-huh.
我错过什么了？这很重要吗？
What am I missing? Why is that important?
因为我们只能二选一
Because we can only do one.
要么按原计划给沃特尼发送食物补给
Send Watney enough food to last till Ares 4...
要么让赫尔墨斯号返回火星，接他回来
or send Hermes back to get him right now.
两个计划都要用到太阳神
Both plans require the Taiyang Shen,
我们只能选择一个
so we have to choose.
赫尔墨斯号的队员们怎么办？
But what about the Hermes crew?
我们这是要求他们
We'd be asking them to add
延长任务533天
533 extra days to their mission.
没错，但是他们绝对不会有丝毫犹豫的
Yeah. They wouldn't hesitate, not for a second.
赫尔墨斯号能在完成任务后继续运行533天吗？
Can the Hermes function for 533 days beyond the scheduled mission end?
应该可以
It should.
它能完成整个战神任务
Built to last the full Ares mission...
所以，现在只达到一半的寿命而已
so technically, it's only halfway through its lifespan.
但是如果出了任何差错
But if something goes wrong...
我们就会失去整个团队
Then we lose the crew.
所以呢，要不就是较大概率
BRUCE: So what? We either have a high chance
牺牲一个人
of killing one person...
要不就是较小概率牺牲六个人
or a low chance of killing six people.
我们要怎么做这种选择？
How do we make that decision?
我们不用做选择，布鲁斯
We don't have to make it, Bruce.
是他来做
He does.
胡说什么
MITCH: Yeah, well, bullshit.
这应该是刘易斯队长的决定
It should be Commander Lewis' call.
可是我们还是有很大机会可以把五个队员平安的带回来
We still have a chance to bring five astronauts home safe and sound.
我不会让他们以身试险
I'm not risking their lives.
让他们自己决定吧
Let them make that decision.
米奇，不用说了，我们采用第一个计划
Mitch, we're going with option one.
你个没种的胆小鬼
You goddamn coward.
他整天都在舱外活动
MINDY: So, he's been doing EVAs throughout the day?
但他们还是有点规律的，这，看这个.
But there's a pattern to them. Here, watch this.
他走了300米然后停下来.
So, he goes 300 meters and then stops.
然后又走了300米停下来.
Then he goes another 300 and stops.
没人给他指令？
Nobody's giving him any instructions?
JPL没有给他定个计划？
JPL didn't schedule something?
没，他在探测车上
No. He's with the Rover.
好，我们刚收到这个
Okay, so we just got this.
化学成分分析样本批次1A7C
Chem analysis sample batch 1A7C.
路易斯队长的燃料组成实验
Commander Lewis' fuel compositing experiments.
(CHUCKLES)
他在继续完成这一次的任务.
He's finishing the mission.
喔.
Wow.
(DISCO MUSIC PLAYING)
31个太阳日的任务只做了18个太阳日就撤了.
We evac'd 18 sols into a 31-sol mission.
这意味着...
Which means...
我们还有13个太阳日的实验和研究值得完成.
we've got 13 sols' worth of experiment and research left to do.
因此，路易斯队长.
So, Commander Lewis...
你的工作交给专家了.
your work is in good hands.
嗨，贝克.
Hey, Beck...
我不理解矿物质营养成分的扫描.
I do not understand chemolithotrophic detection.
我是说完全不理解.
I mean, at all.
But I'm working on it, working my way through it.
嗨，约翰森.
Hey, Johanssen...
我知道你不喜欢别人碰你的化学分析仪.
I know you don't like it when I touch the ChemCam.
但是.
But...
老子就摸了化学分析仪.
I'm touching the ChemCam.
摸了好几次.
A lot.
沃格尔，你的核心样本
Vogel, your core samples...
在专家手上
in very good hands.
实际上
Actually...
我想我给核心样本找到了一个
I think I found a new cataloguing system...
新的分类系统
for the core samples.
我已经把它命名为“老爹核心样本”
I've actually titled it “Das Core Samples"
出于对祖国的尊敬
out of respect for the fatherland.
最后，马丁内兹...
And finally, Martinez...
我都不知道你到底做的是什么.
I'm still not sure what it is that you do.
向上帝发誓，我真的不能告诉你
Honest to God, I really couldn't tell you.
我都不知道我们带你来干嘛.
I don't know why we brought you.
就这样
That's it.
不管怎样，我尽力把所有事情都记录下来，分类好.
Anyway, I'm trying to keep everything documented, organized.
我知道这不是我的强项
I know it's not my strong suit...
但我想让一切都变得有意义
but I do want everything to make sense.
只是防止事情不按我的方式来进行.
Just in case things don't break my way.
实际上，你某一天可能会在课堂上讲这一切.
Actually, you could teach all this in a class someday.
比如，好的一面，像如何用NASA的管子和同位素发电机.
You know, the good stuff, like how to make a bathtub...
做一个淋浴间.
using NASA tubing and an old RTG.
如何用6000种方式烤土豆.
How to cook a potato about 6,000 different ways.
马克·沃特尼的教学大纲.
The Mark Watney syllabus.
- 约翰森，你在吗？- 我在
VOGEL: Johanssen? Yeah.
我知道现在是私人时间，但是我能打扰你一下吗？
I know it's your private time. Can I bother you for a second?
可以，说吧
JOHANSSEN: Yeah, go ahead.
你在哪里？
VOGEL: Where are you?
健身房
The gym.
(BEEPS)
(PANTING)
什么事？
What's up?
我老婆给我的一封邮件
I just got an email from my wife
主题栏写的是“我们的孩子”
and the subject line says, "Our children."
但是我的电脑打不开附件
My computer won't open the attachment.
好的
Okay.
我来看看
Let's take a look.
呃...
Uh...
看一下
Let's see.
这不是图片文件
This isn't a JPEG.
只是个ASCII码文本文件
It's a plain ASCII text file.
我不知道这文件什么意思
I don't really know what we're looking at.
你能看懂吗？
Does that make any sense to you?
里奇·珀内尔机动策略
"Rich Purnell Maneuver."
这是新的赫尔墨斯号航线策略
It's a course maneuver for the Hermes.
这个任务要求在第211个太阳日终止
And the mission concludes with Earth intercept,
与地球对接
211 days later.
这个计划能行吗？
MARTINEZ: Would it work?
我们测试了数据，没有问题
LEWIS: Mmm-hmm. We ran the numbers. They check out.
这个计划太聪明了
BECK: It's a brilliant course.
那为什么我们还要秘密行动？
So why all the cloak and dagger?
因为航天局不允许我们这么做
Because it goes directly against NASA's decision.
没错，但是如果我们这么做了
Yeah. If we do the maneuver,
他们别无他法，只能给我们发送补给
they'd have to send the supply ship or we die.
所以我们有机会改变他们的决定
We have the opportunity to force their hand.
所以呢，我们要做吗？
So, are we gonna do it?
如果是我来决定，我们早就在去火星的路上了
If it was up to me, we'd already be on our way.
但这就是你能决定的事啊
But it is, though, isn't it? Up to you.
这次不行
(CHUCKLES) Not this time.
这个计划被航天局否决了
This is something NASA expressly rejected.
如果行动，就是违抗命令
We're talking about mutiny here,
所以我不能一个人决定
which is not a word that I take lightly.
要么大家都同意，要么放弃
So we do this together or not at all.
在你答应之前，想想这次行动的后果
And before you answer, consider the consequences.
如果补给对接失败，我们会没命
If we mess up the supply rendezvous, we die.
如果借助地球引力助推失败，我们也会没命
If we mess up the Earth gravity assist, we die.
就算一切都没问题
If we do everything perfectly...
我们要延长任务533天
we add 533 days to our mission.
533天以后才能再次和家人团聚
533 more days before we see our families again.
533天计划外的太空行程
533 days of unplanned space travel...
一切都有可能出差错
where anything could go wrong.
如果任务没成功，我们还是会没命
If it's mission critical, we die.
算上我
Sign me up.
别激动，牛仔.
All right, cowboy, slow down.
你和我都是军人
You and I, we're military.
我们回去就有可能上军事法庭
Chances are, we go home, they'll court martial us.
是有这个可能
Yeah, there's that.
至于其他人
LEWIS: And for the rest of you guys...
我确信，他们不可能再让你们参与太空任务了
I guarantee they will never send you back up here again.
明白了，如果我们答应的话，计划怎么执行？
Good. So, if we go for it, how would it work?
我来制定航线，并负责执行
I plot the course and execute it.
远程操控
JOHANSSEN: Remote override.
他们完全可以从任务指挥中心
They could take over the Hermes
来远程控制赫尔墨斯号
from Mission Control.
你能解除吗？
LEWIS: Can you disable it?
赫尔墨斯号有4台备用计算机
Hermes has four redundant flight computers...
每台计算机又连接3个备用通讯系统
each connected to three redundant comm systems.
如果关掉通讯系统
We can't shut down the comms
就失去了遥测和导航功能
because we'd lose telemetry and guidance.
如果关掉计算机
And we can't shut down the computers
整个飞船都无法运行
because we need to run the ship.
这样我得解除每个系统的远程操控
I'd have to disable remote override on each system.
所以我得想办法跳过系统代码
It's part of the OS, I'd have to jump over the code.
好了，说人话，你能做到吗？
Okay, but, like, in English, what would that mean?
我能做到
I can do it.
很好
Great.
并且，这必须是集体同意
Well, it has to be unanimous.
如果这么做的话，在太空就要待上900多天
If we do this, it'll be over 900 days of space.
一辈子的太空任务加起来也没这么多
That's more than enough space for one life...
所以，我同意
so, yes.
我也同意
I vote yes.
我们去接他回家
Let's go get him.
约翰森呢？
Johanssen?
同意
Yes.
太好了！
Yeah! (ALL CHEERING)
(APPLAUSE)
沃特尼，我们来救你
接收到新的文本消息
但是你们打算怎么做呢
But how are you gonna do that?
赫尔墨斯号有计划外的状态更新
Got an unscheduled status update from Hermes.
收到，读出来
BRENDAN: Roger. Read it out.
“休斯顿，请注意”
Message reads, "Houston, please be advised.
“里奇·珀内尔是个绝妙的天才”
"Rich Purnell is a steely-eyed missile man."
什么？
What?
指挥官，导航台
GUIDANCE TECHNICIAN: Flight, Guidance.
检测到赫尔墨斯号偏离航线
Hermes is off-course.
通讯员，通知他们已偏离航线
CAPCOM, advise Hermes they're drifting.
导航台，准备纠正航线
Guidance, get a correction ready.
无法纠正，指挥官
GUIDANCE TECHNICIAN: Negative, Flight,
不是航线偏离，而是他们改变了航线
it's not drift. They've adjusted course.
什么情况？
What the hell?
遥测台，有没有可能是仪表故障？
Telemetry, any chance this is instrumentation failure?
不是仪表问题，指挥官
Negative, Flight
导航台，计算下要挽回这件事情
Guidance, work at how long they can stay
我们还剩多少时间
on this course before it's irreversible.
正在计算，指挥官
GUIDANCE TECHNICIAN: Working on that now, Flight.
谁是里奇·珀内尔？
(WHISPERS) Hey. Who's Rich Purnell?
我不知道
I don't know.
谁能告诉我这个里奇·珀内尔到底是谁？
Will somebody find out who the hell Rich Purnell is?
安妮今早会通知媒体
SANDERS: Annie will go before the media this morning...
航天局作出决定
and inform them of NASA's decision
让赫尔墨斯号重返火星
to reroute the Hermes to Mars.
挺明智的决定
Sounds like a smart move.
考虑到他们已经这么做的情况下
Considering the circumstances.
无论是谁通知了他们都没关系
Whoever gave them the maneuver only passed along information.
因为这个决定是他们自己做的
Crew made the decision on their own.
他们可能因为你而丧命，米奇
You may have killed them, Mitch.
我们坐的是同一条船
We're fighting the same war.
每次出现问题
Every time something goes wrong,
外界就不管初衷，把我们一棒子打死
the world forgets why we fly.
我只是想保住我们的航天事业
I'm trying to keep us airborne.
这比一个人的生命重要
It's bigger than one person.
不
No.
不是
It's not.
等这件事结束，我希望能看到你的辞职信
When this is over, I'll expect your resignation.
我明白
I understand.
把他们都带回来吧
Bring our astronauts home.
第219个太阳日
每个战神任务都会提前三年准备物资
Every Ares mission requires three years of pre-supplies.
所以航天局早就决定
So NASA decided a long time ago it's a lot easier...
预先送一些设备到火星
to send some of the stuff beforehand
这样比我们自己带过来容易得多
rather than bring it with us.
所以，战神4号的飞行器
So, as a result, the MAV for Ares 4...
已经在任务地点
is already there
夏帕雷利环形山那里了
at the Schiaparelli Crater, just waiting.
所以新计划就是，我乘飞行器到达火星轨道
So the plan is for me to use that to go into orbit...
此时赫尔墨斯号正好经过
just as the Hermes is passing...
然后我猜，他们会接住我？
and I guess they catch me?
太空对接
In space.
所以我有200天的时间来计划
So, I've got 200 sols to figure out...
如何带上生命补给系统
how to take everything here that's keeping me alive...
比如氧合器，水回收器
the oxygenator, the water reclaimer,
大气调节器等等
the atmospheric regulator...
所有的一切
bring that all with me.
幸好，地球上有一群人
And luckily, I have the greatest minds
也在想办法
on Planet Earth...
而且他们是各个领域的专家
really, all of the brainpower on the entire planet...
一起帮我实现这个计划
helping me with this endeavor.
目前他们想出的办法就是
And so far they've come up with...
在探测车顶
"Hey, why don't you drill holes
钻出一圈的洞
"on the roof of your Rover...
然后使劲的把车顶砸下来
"and hit it as hard as you can with a rock?"
我们会成功的
We're gonna get there.
(STARMAN PLAYING)
BMG: 大卫·鲍伊－星星小子
BMG: David Bowie－Starman
(GROANS)
证件
Your ID，please.
不知道现在是什么时候
Didn't know what time it was
灯光变得昏暗
And the lights were low
我靠在我的收音机上
I leaned back on my radio
(ALL SPEAKING MAN DARIN)
几只猫开始躺下，几只猫开始摇滚出...
Some cat was layin' down some rock 'n' roll
...许多灵魂,  他说
Lotta soul, he said
那么响亮的声音似乎消逝
Then the loud sound did seem to fade
回来像一个缓慢的声音在一个阶段波动
Came back like a slow voice on a wave of phase
这里还没有DJ,  这是朦胧的太空牛仔舞
That weren't no DJ That was hazy cosmic jive
再见，火星
有一个星星小子在太空中等待
There's a starman waiting in the sky
还要533天？
533 days longer?
你居然答应了？
And you said yes to this?
他也会为我这么做的
He would have done the same for me. You know that.
(BOY LAUGHING)
说“茄子”吧？
Cheese. You do "cheese"?
茄子
Cheese. (CAMERA CLICKS)
他没说“茄子”
He didn't do "cheese."
他说了吗？
Did he do "cheese"?
(GRUNTING)
嗨，宝贝儿
ROBERT: Hey, baby.
嘿
Hey-
我给你准备了个礼物
I got something for you.
在跳蚤市场找到的
Found it in the flea market.
第一版
Original pressing.
不是吧！
LEWIS: No!
(EXCLAIMS JOYFULLY)
没有一点儿划痕
Not a scratch.
我太喜欢了
I love it.
我无意冒犯你们的政策
All due respect to your CNSA protocol...
但是我们自从阿波罗9号以来
but we haven't done things that way...
就没这么做过
since Apollo 9.
(TRANSLATING INTO MAN DARIN)
他明白吗？
Did he get that?
透过你的窗户，我能看见他的星光
Look out your window I can see his light
如果我们能闪光，他可能今晚着陆
If we can sparkle He may land tonight
TECHNICIAN: Mmm-hmm. Yeah. Mmm-hmm.
Mmm-hmm.
Oh!
有一个星星小子在太空中等待
There's a starman waiting in the sky
(KIDS LAUGHING)
他想过来和我们见面
He'd like to come and meet us
但他想他可能会让我们惊讶
But he thinks he'd blow our minds
有一个星星小子在太空中等待
There's a starman waiting in the sky
5...4...3...
(COUNTING DOWN IN MANDARIN ON PA)
他告诉我们，不要搞砸了
He's told us not to blow it
因为他知道这一切都值得
'Cause he knows it's all worthwhile
他告诉我让孩子们丢掉他
He told me Let the children lose it
让孩子们用他，让所有的孩子随着音乐起舞
Let the children use it Let all the children boogie
(ALL CHEERING)
有一个星星小子在太空中等待
There's a starman waiting in the sky
他想过来和我们见面
He'd like to come and meet us
但他想他可能会让我们惊讶
But he thinks he'd blow our minds
有一个星星小子在太空中等待
There's a starman waiting in the sky
他告诉我们，不要搞砸了
He's told us not to blow it
因为他知道这一切都值得
'Cause he knows it's all worthwhile
他告诉我让孩子们丢掉他
He told me Let the children lose it
让孩子们用他
Let the children use it
让所有的孩子随着音乐起舞
Let all the children boogie
啦, 啦, 啦, 啦, 啦, 啦, 啦, 啦
La, Ia, la, Ia, la, Ia, la, la
(AIRLOCK HISSING)
7个月后
第461个太阳日
我一直在想火星的法律问题
WATNEY: I've been thinking about laws on Mars.
有这样一则国际条约
There's an international treaty
说任何国家都不能宣称拥有
saying no country can lay claim...
非地球的一切资源
to anything that's not on Earth.
还有另一则条约
And by another treaty,
说如果你所在的领地不属于任何国家
if you're not in any country's territory...
海洋法就可以适用
maritime law applies.
所以火星就相当于国际海域
So Mars is international waters.
而航天局是一个美国的非军事组织
Now, NASA is an American non-military organization.
居住舱属于他们
It owns the Hab.
但是只要我出了居住舱，我就在公海领域上了
But the second I walk outside, I'm in international waters.
接下来的事情就有意思了
So here's the cool part.
我就要出发去夏帕雷利环形山
I'm about to leave for the Schiaparelli Crater...
并征用战神4号的着陆器
where I'm gonna commandeer the Ares 4 lander.
没有人准许我这么做
Nobody explicitly gave me permission to do this...
除非我是战神4任务的一员
and they can't until I'm on board the Ares 4.
这就意味着，我就要在国际海域上
So that means I'm gonna be taking a craft over...
非法占有一个太空飞行器
in international waters without permission.
也就是说，我成了一名海盗
Which, by definition, makes me a pirate.
马克·沃特尼，太空海盗
Mark Watney, Space Pirate.
你是个太空海盗
A Space Pirate.
无论到哪里，我都是史上第一人
Everywhere I go, I'm the first.
这种感觉很奇怪
It's a strange feeling.
离开探测车
Step outside the Rover...
我就是到那里的第一个人
first guy to be there.
爬上那座小山，我还是第一个
Climb that hill, first guy to do that.
45亿年以来
Four and a half billion years...
这里空无一人
nobody here.
现在，我来了
And now, me.
我是独自拥有整个星球的第一人
I'm the first person to be alone on an entire planet.
(INDISTINCT RADIO CHATTER)
情况如何？
How's he doing?
(CLEARS THROAT)
目前一切正常
So far, so good.
他一直按着时间表行动
He's sticking to schedule.
中午前开车4小时
Drives for four hours before noon...
铺好太阳能电池板
lays the solar panels,
等13个小时的充电时间
waits 13 hours for them to recharge...
在某个地方睡一会儿，然后继续启程
and sleeps somewhere in there and then starts again.
他怎么样了？
How's he doing?
他叫我们喊他金胡子船长
He asked us to call him Captain Blondebeard.
是没错，按理说火星相当于公海领域…
Well, technically, Mars would be under maritime...
我知道，他给我们说过了
Yeah, I know. He explained it to us.
他在哪里？
Where is he?
那儿  - 好的
There. Okay.
等下
Here.
好的
Okay.
第494个太阳日
(BEEPING)
(BEEPS)
第517个太阳日
好的，我先声明
Okay, I'm gonna start by stating for the record
你不会喜欢这个主意的
that you're not gonna like this.
是么？
VINCENT: Oh, yeah?
没错，问题出在对接速度上
Yeah, the problem is the intercept velocity.
赫尔墨斯号，不能进入火星轨道
The Hermes, well... It can't enter Mars' orbit.
不然，挣脱火星引力会消耗大量燃料，他们也就回不来了
Otherwise, they'll never have enough fuel to make it home.
火星飞行器的设计
The MAV, that was only designed
只能让它达到火星低空轨道
to get to low Mars orbit.
为了让马克能完全挣脱火星的引力
So in order for Mark to escape Mars' gravity entirely...
并和赫尔墨斯号对接
and to intercept the Hermes...
- 他必须速度更快  - 正是如此
He has to be going fast. Exactly.
所以，我们得降低飞行器的重量
Which means we need to make the MAV lighter.
降低的不是一点点重量，而是5000公斤
A lot lighter. 5,000 kilograms lighter.
这个你们能做到的，对吧？
You can do that, right?
有些重量是可以毫不费力就能去掉的
There's some gimmes right off the bat.
比如，飞行器本来要携带500公斤的火星土壤和其他样本
The design presumes 500 kilograms of Martian soil and samples.
显然，这个可以直接省掉
Obviously we won't do that.
而且现在只有一个宇航员，而不是六个
And there's just one passenger instead of six.
宇航服和装备，又能去掉500公斤对吗？
With suits and gear, that's another 500?
生命补给系统也可以丢掉
Ditch the life support, don't need it.
整个过程中，我们会让马克穿着舱外宇航服
And we'll get Mark to wear his EVA suit the whole trip.
等等，如果让他穿舱外宇航服
Wait a second. If he's in his EVA suit,
他要怎么控制飞行器？
how is he gonna operate the controls?
他不用控制
Well, he won't.
马丁内兹会从赫尔墨斯号遥控飞行器
Martinez will pilot the MAV remotely from the Hermes.
我们从没尝试过远程控制载人飞船
We've never had a manned ship controlled remotely before.
但是有这个机会
(SIGHS) But I am excited about
我还是比较想尝试一下
the opportunities that affords.
如果确定远程控制，就可以丢掉控制面板
If we go remote, we can lose the control panels,
二级和三级通讯系统
the secondary and tertiary comm systems.
等一下
VINCENT: Wait a second.
备用通讯系统你们也要去掉？
You want a remote-controlled ascent with no backup comms?
这还不是最糟糕的，文森特
He's not even got to the bad stuff yet, Vincent.
那就直接说什么是最糟糕的！
Let's skip to the bad stuff!
我们打算去掉气密舱顶板
We need to remove the nose airlock,
窗户和19号舱板
the windows, and Hull Panel 19.
你要把飞行器整个顶部拿掉？
You want to take the front of the ship off?
没错
BRUCE: Sure.
单是气密舱顶板就重达400公斤
The nose airlock alone is 400 kilograms.
你想让他坐着敞篷飞船上太空？
You want to send a man into space without the front of his ship?
不是
Well, no.
我们可以在飞行器顶部盖上帆布
We're gonna have him cover it with Hab canvas.
舱板大部分作用是为了保持空气流通
Look, the hull's mostly there to keep the air in.
火星的空气稀薄
Mars' atmosphere is so thin,
舱体不是流线型也可以
you don't need a lot of streamlining.
等飞船的速度逐渐加快
By the time the ship's going fast enough
空气阻力开始产生作用时
for air resistance to matter...
这时候飞船所在的高度已经几乎没有空气了
it'll be high enough that there's practically no air.
你要让他顶着帆布上太空
You wanna send him into space under a tarp.
是的
Yes.
我能继续了吗？
Can I go on?
不
No.
你觉得他这句话的语气是…
You think he means it like...
“你是逗我玩儿吧？”
"Are you kidding me?"
- 这样的 - 嗯嗯
You know? Mmm-hmm.
还是，“你他妈开什么玩笑？”
Or like, "Are you kidding me?"
我猜可能是第二种
I think it might be the second one.
- 是吗？- 嗯嗯
Really? Uh-huh.
也有可能是第一种啊
Could be the first way.
“你是逗我玩儿吧？”
"Are you kidding me?"
是啊，也有可能是第一种
Yeah, it could be the first way.
第524个太阳日
第538个太阳日
夏帕雷利环形山
战神4号着陆点
我知道他们的小把戏
WATNEY: I know what they're doing.
而且知道得一清二楚
I know exactly what they're doing.
他们一直重复这句话
They just keep repeating...
“你将成为太空飞行史上最快之人”
"Go faster than any man in the history of space travel."
让我听起来像是件好事
Like that's a good thing.
其实是想转移我的注意力
Like it'll distract me from how insane their plan is.
没错，我是可以即将成为
Yeah, I get to go faster than any man
太空飞行史上速度最快的人
in the history of space travel...
那是因为你们让我坐在敞篷车里上太空
because you are launching me in a convertible.
其实比坐敞篷车更糟
Actually it's worse than that
因为我根本没法控制这玩意儿
because I won't even be able to control the thing.
顺便说一下，地球的物理学家们
And by the way, physicists,
你们在描述加速的物体时
when describing things like acceleration...
不要用“非常快”这样的字眼
do not use the word "fast."
他们这样做，是希望
So they're only doing that in the hopes
我不要对这个疯狂计划
that I won't raise any objections...
提出反对意见
to this lunacy.
他们以为我会喜欢听这句话
Because I like the way
“你将成为太空飞行史上最快之人”
"fastest man in the history of space travel" sounds.
我的确喜欢
I do like the way it sounds.
事实是，我非常喜欢
I mean, I like it a lot.
不过我不会告诉他们的
I'm not gonna tell them that.
(SIGHS)
好吧
Okay-
开始行动吧
Let's do this.
(WATERLOO PLAYING)
BMG: 阿巴乐队－滑铁卢
BMG: ABBA－Waterloo
我，我，
My, my
在滑铁卢，拿破仑投降的地方
At Waterloo Napoleon did surrender
哦，是的
Oh, yeah
我也遇到了我的命运颇为相似的方式
And I have met my destiny in quite a similar way
在书架上的历史书总是重演
The history book on the shelf is always repeating itself
滑铁卢
Waterloo
我被打败了，你赢得了战争
I was defeated You won the war
快点儿啊
Come on.
滑铁卢, 无限永远爱你更多
Waterloo, promise to love you forevermore
滑铁卢, 无法逃避，如果我想
Waterloo Couldn't escape if I wanted to
滑铁卢
Waterloo
知道我的命运是和你在一起
Knowing my fate is to be with you
哦, 哦, 哦, 哦, 滑铁卢
Oh, oh, oh, oh, Waterloo
终于要面对我的滑铁卢
Finally facing my Waterloo
我, 我
My, my
我试过握着你回来，
I tried to hold you back
但你更强
But you were stronger
哦，对了，
Oh, yeah
现在看来我唯一的机会就是放弃战斗
And now it seems my only chance is giving up the fight
而且我怎么能拒绝过?
And how could I ever refuse?
我在失败的时候感觉到了胜利
I feel like I win when I lose
滑铁卢
Waterloo
我被打败了，你赢得了战争
I was defeated You won the war
滑铁卢
Waterloo
无限永远爱你更多
Promise to love you forevermore
滑铁卢
Waterloo
无法逃避，如果我想
Couldn't escape if I wanted to
(STRAINING)
滑铁卢
Waterloo
知道我的命运是和你在一起
Knowing my fate is to be with you
哦, 哦, 哦, 哦, 滑铁卢
Oh, oh, oh, oh, Waterloo
终于要面对我的滑铁卢
Finally facing my Waterloo
所以，我怎么能拒绝过
So how could I ever refuse?
我在失败的时候感觉到了胜利
I feel like I win when I lose
滑铁卢
Waterloo
无法逃避，如果我想
Couldn't escape if I wanted to
你又害死他了
And you killed him.
再试一次.
Try it again.
哦, 滑铁卢
Ooh, Waterloo
知道我的命运是和你在一起
Finally facing my Waterloo
哦, 哦, 哦, 哦, 滑铁卢
Oh, oh, oh, oh, Waterloo
第560个太阳日
你害死他多少次了？
How many times you kill Watney?
重要的是我已经尝试过进入轨道之后的所有场景.
The important thing is that I got all scenarios into orbit.
这才是重要的事.
That's the important thing.
他准备好了.    好吧
He's ready. LEWIS: Okay.
计划是这样的
Here's the plan.
马丁内兹遥控飞行器，
Martinez flies the MAV.
约翰森操控升空过程
Johanssen sysops the ascent.
贝克，沃格尔，外舱门打开时你们要到2号气密舱那里
Beck, Vogel, I want you guys in Airlock 2 with the outer door open...
- 这是在飞行器发射之前- 好的
before the MAV even launches. Okay.
一旦可以对接，贝克负责去接沃特尼
Once we hit intercept, it's Beck's job to go get Watney.
接到他的时候，他的情况可能会很差
He may be in bad shape when we get him.
敞篷的飞行器在发射过程中会产生12个G的加速度
The stripped-down MAV will get him to 12 G's during the launch.
他可能会昏过去，甚至内出血.
He could be knocked unconscious, may even have internal bleeding.
好在你是我们的医生.
Well, it's a good thing you're our doctor.
对接计划是什么？
What's the intercept plan?
我们把缆绳拼接起来
We finished attaching the tethers into one long line.
有214米长
It's 214 meters long.
加上使用太空漫步装置，行动应该很容易
And I'll have the MMU, so moving around should be easy.
你能接受多大的相对速度？
How fast a relative velocity can you handle?
5米每秒的情况下我可以抓住飞行器
I can grab the MAV at 5 meters per second.
10米每秒的话，我相当于跳上一辆行驶的火车
10 is like jumping onto a moving train.
再快的话就可能会失败
So any more than that and I might miss.
我们有一些时间可以调整
Well, we may have some leeway.
发射过程需要12分钟
The launch takes 12 minutes.
对接前还有52分钟时间
And it'll be 52 minutes before intercept.
一旦飞行器的引擎关闭
Once Mark's engine shuts off...
我们就能知道对接位置和速度了
we'll know our intercept point and velocity.
沃格尔，你充当贝克的后援
Vogel, you're Beck's backup.
一切顺利的话，你用缆绳拉他们俩回来
Everything goes well, you pull them on board with the tether.
如果有什么差错，你在贝克之后行动
If anything goes wrong, you go out after him.
没问题
VOGEL: Yep.
好的
LEWIS: Okay.
我们去接他回家吧
Let's go get our boy.
第561个太阳日
无论是谁看到，请好好照看这辆车，它曾救过我的命
—沃特尼
大批群众焦虑而又紧张地聚集在
REPORTER: There's a mood of tension and anxiety here,
约翰逊太空中心外
outside Johnson Space Center.
可以看到
As you can see,
大家都来到这里
many people have gathered here...
迫切关注
to see whether or not
拯救马克·沃特尼的行动能否成功
the mission to retrieve Mark Watney will be a success.
航天局已经和马克有所联系
They've had some contact with him,
时代广场，纽约
在此，我们提醒观众
We have to remind our viewers
我们会持续关注行动的进展
that we're watching this as it unfolds.
并时刻向您汇报
So we'll try and keep you up-to-date
拯救行动的具体细节
as to what exactly is going on.
现在，让我们带你们走进现场听听航天局和马克·沃特尼的联系情况
Let's listen in to NASA making contact with Mark Watney.
我们听一下
Let's listen in.
如果他们那边出了问题，我们能做什么？
If something goes wrong, what can Mission Control do?
什么也做不了
Not a damn thing.
我们和他们的距离太远
It's all happening 12 light-minutes away...
无论他们问了什么问题
which means it takes 24 minutes for them
都得24分钟后才能收到这边的回答
to get the answer to any question they ask.
整个发射需要12分钟
The whole launch is 12 minutes...
接下来他们只能靠自己了
so they're on their own.
(HISSING IN PAIN)
(WHIRRING)
中国国家航天局总部，北京
(WOMAN SPEAKING MANDARIN ON PA)
特拉法加广场，伦敦
...马克究竟有多长时间
REPORTER: ...just how long Mark has been
一个人在火星上.
completely alone on Mars.
我们稍后会同心理学专家讨论...
We're talking to a psychology expert later to discuss...
燃油压力，正常
JOHANSSEN: Fuel pressure, green.
发动机校准，正常
Engine alignment, perfect.
通讯系统，准备就绪
Communications, five by five.
可以准备起飞检查了，队长
We are ready for pre-flight checklist, Commander.
指挥中心，这里是赫尔墨斯号
LEWIS: Mission Control, this is Hermes actual.
我们即将按计划行动
We will proceed on schedule.
距离发射时间
We are T-minus 2 minutes, 10 seconds
还有2分10秒
to launch, by the mark.
还有2分钟左右，沃特尼
About two minutes, Watney.
你那边还好吗？
How you doing down there?
我很好
I'm good.
希望能快点见到你们
I'm anxious to get up to you.
谢谢你们为我回来
Thanks for coming back for me.
我们准备就绪
LEWIS: Well, we're on it.
一会儿你会经历超重飞行
Remember, you'll be pulling some serious G's,
所以有可能会昏厥
so it's okay to pass out.
你的命运就在马丁内兹手里了
You're in Martinez's hands now.
告诉那小子别给我玩特技
Well, tell that asshole no barrel rolls.
(LAUGHS)
收到
Copy that, MAV.
通讯员
CAPCOM.
准备就绪
JOHANSSEN: Go.
远程指挥
LEWIS: Remote command. (CRYING)
就绪
MARTINEZ: Go.
对接员
LEWIS: Recovery.
就绪
BECK: Go.
后补对接员
LEWIS: Secondary recovery.
就绪
VOGEL: Go.
飞行员
Pilot.
准备就绪
Go.
飞行员
LEWIS: Pilot.
准备就绪
WATNEY: Go. (ALL CHEERING)
收到，准备起飞
MISSION CONTROL TECHNICIAN: Copy. We're go.
指挥中心，我们准备发射
LEWIS: Mission Control, we are go for launch.
倒计时10
T-minus ten...
nine...
主引擎启动
Main engine start.
JOHANSSEN: eight...
seven...
解除飞行器固定
Mooring clamps released.
还有5秒钟，沃特尼，撑住
About five seconds, Watney. Hang on.
一会儿见，队长
I'll see you in a few, Commander.
JOHANSSEN: four...
three...
two...
one.
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
速度，每秒741米
JOHANSSEN: Velocity, 741 meters per second.
高度，1350米
Altitude, 1350 meters.
太低了
That's too low.
我控制不了
It's fighting me.
沃特尼，能收到吗？
LEWIS: (ECHOING) Watney, do you read?
(GROANING SOFTLY)
助推器分离
MARTINEZ: Booster separation complete.
速度，850，高度，1843
Velocity, 850. Altitude, 1843.
还是在目标高度以下
He's well below target altitude.
高度差多少？
How far below?
计算中
JOHANSSEN: Checking.
沃特尼
Watney.
能听到吗？
Do you read?
他可能失去意识了
BECK: He's probably passed out.
重力已经达到了12个g
He pulled 12 g's on the ascent.
给他点时间
Give him a few minutes.
明白
LEWIS: Copy that.
主引擎准备关闭，3
JOHANSSEN: Main shutdown in three...
2，1
two, one...
关闭
shutdown.
启用自动导航模式
MARTINEZ: Back to automatic guidance.
引擎关闭确认
Shutdown confirmed.
燃料储备耗尽
Fuel reserves depleted.
沃特尼？
LEWIS: Watney?
能听到吗？
Do you read?
传输可能出现了
It seems there's some sort of problem
一些问题
with the transmission.
数据已返回
JOHANSSEN: I have interval pings.
对接速度为11米每秒
Intercept velocity will be 11 meters per second.
我可以办到
I can make that work.
对接时相距…
JOHANSSEN: Distance at intercept will be...
68千米
We'll be 68 kilometers apart.
68千米？
BECK: 68 kilometers?
她是说68千米吗？
Did she just say 68 kilometers?
各位，团结起来
Come on, guys, keep it together.
解决问题
Work the problem.
约翰森，还有多少时间对接？
Johanssen, time to intercept?
39分12秒
JOHANSSEN: 39 minutes, 12 seconds.
马丁内兹，可以把推进器
Martinez, what if we point our thrusters
都对准一个方向吗？
in the same direction?
要看你想省下多少燃料
Well, it depends how much fuel you wanna save...
用于调整高度和返程
for the altitude adjustments for the trip home.
你认为需要多少？
How much do you need?
给我目前剩余的20%就可以
I can get by with about 20% of what we have left.
如果用调整高度燃料的75.5%
If we use 75.5% of remaining altitude-adjust fuel...
就可以将对接距离差降到零
that will bring the intercept range to zero.
就这么做
Do it.
等等，距离差为零
Hang on. it brings the range to zero...
但是速度却达到了42米每秒
but the intercept velocity will be 42 meters per second.
这个速度太快
And that's way too fast.
那我们还有39分钟想办法
Then we'll have 39 minutes to figure out
把速度降下来
how to slow down.
马丁内兹，打开喷气机
Martinez, burn the jets.
收到
MARTINEZ: Copy that.
呼叫赫尔墨斯号
MAV to Hermes.
沃特尼，是你吗？
LEWIS: Watney?
是我
WATNEY: Affirmative.
(ALL CHEERING)
你现在情况如何？
LEWIS: What's your status?
我的胸很痛
WATNEY: My chest hurts.
肋骨断了几根
I broke my ribs.
你们怎么样？
How are you?
我们正在想办法救你
LEWIS: We're working on getting to you.
发射过程出现了一些问题
There was a complication during launch.
收到
Copy that.
问题严重吗？
How bad is it?
我们修正了对接距离
LEWIS: We've corrected the intercept range,
但是对接速度有很大问题
but we've got a problem with intercept velocity.
速度是多少？
WATNEY: How big a problem?
42米每秒
42 meters a second.
那可真是…
Well...
操蛋
Shit.
队长，我有个主意
Commander, I have an idea.
说来听听
LEWIS: Go ahead, Mark.
如果我用个尖锐物品
Well, if I can find something sharp in here...
在我的手套上戳个洞
and poke a hole in the glove of my EVA suit...
我就可以用泄露的气体当助推器
I could use the escaping air as a thruster...
朝你们飞过去
and fly towards you.
因为这个就在我手上，所以比较容易控制
It would be easy to control because it would be on my arm.
我不觉得你这么做能控制任何东西
LEWIS: I can't see you having any control if you did that.
这样做只能目测进行对接
You'd be eyeballing the intercept
而且推力矢量也无法控制
using a thrust vector you can barely control.
没错，你说得很对
Yes, those are all very good points.
但是想想
But consider this.
我却可以像钢铁侠一样到处飞了
I'd get to fly around like Iron Man.
(JOHANSSEN LAUGHS)
队长
WATNEY: Commander...
让我当钢铁侠吧
let's go Iron Man.
信号意外丢失
NASA TECHNICIAN 1: This is unexpected LOS.
通讯信号丢失，待命中
NASA TECHNICIAN 2: Communication lost. Stand by.
这主意也许不坏
Maybe it's not the worst idea.
不，这主意坏透了，糟透了
No, it is the worst idea. It's the worst idea ever.
不是他说的那些
Not what he said.
而是用气体当推力
Using atmosphere as thrust.
如果我们可以向前产生一个推力呢？
What happens if we blow the VAL?
你是要打开气密舱吗？
Wait, you want to open the vehicular airlock?
这样可以产生反冲力
It'll give us a good kick.
但是也会把整个飞船的东西都吹走
But also blow the nose off the ship.
而且空气耗尽，我们也就完蛋了
And all the air would leave and we need air to not die.
我们可以封锁舱桥和堆舱
We would seal the bridge and the reactor room.
其他地方会变成真空
Everywhere else would go vacuo.
沃格尔
Vogel.
请讲，队长
VOGEL: Go ahead, Commander.
我需要你回来造个…炸弹
I need you to come inside and make a... bomb.
队长，你说什么？
Again, Commander?
你是个化学家
LEWIS: You're a chemist.
你能用现有的东西造个炸弹吗？
Can you make a bomb with what you have on board?
也许吧
Probably.
但我不得不提醒大家
But I feel obliged to mention
在飞船上引爆一个炸弹
that setting off an explosive device...
这实在是太不明智的行为了
in a spacecraft is a terrible, terrible idea.
等等，你们造炸弹不叫上我？
Hang on. You guys making a bomb without me?
我明白，你能做到吗？
LEWIS: Copy that. Can you do it?
可以
Ja.
休斯顿，请注意
LEWIS: Houston, be advised.
我们准备有计划地制造一个飞船缺口
We are going to deliberately breach the VAL
来产生反向推力
to produce a reverse thrust.
贝克，去1号气密舱和约翰森碰头
Beck, leave your suit on. Meet Johanssen in Airlock 1.
我们会把外舱门打开
We'll open the outer door.
你需要把炸弹放置在内舱门上
I need you to place the charge on the inner door.
然后顺舱体回到2号气密舱
Climb back to Airlock 2 along the hull.
收到，行动中
BECK: Copy. I'm on my way.
我进来了，队长
I'm in, Commander.
收到
LEWIS: Copy that.
沃格尔，你在哪里？
Vogel, where are you?
我在厨房
VOGEL: I'm in the kitchen.
好的
Okay.
队长
WATNEY: Commander...
我不能让你这么做
I can't let you go through with this.
我准备实施我的计划
I am prepared to cut the suit.
绝对不行
Absolutely not.
你瞧，我这人很自私的
WATNEY: See, the thing is, I'm selfish.
我希望地球只给我一个人办追悼会
I want all the memorials back home to be about me.
只纪念我一个人
Just me.
我应该把你留在火星才对
I should have left this guy on Mars.
我来了
Hey-
白糖？
Sugar?
是的
Yeah.
你能拿着这个吗？
Can you hold this?
液态氧
Liquid oxygen...
加上含氨的去污剂
and some stain remover that contains ammonia.
这个东西比一般炸药
This thing here is five times stronger
的威力强5倍
than a stick of dynamite.
怎么才能启动它呢？
How do we activate it?
把它连接到照明控制器上就行了
Can you connect this to one of our lighting panels?
小心点
Careful.
打开1号气密舱
BECK: Open Airlock 1.
我现在去和贝克碰头
JOHANSSEN: I'm on the way to Beck.
希望这是个好主意
Let's just hope this is a good idea, guys.
这就是个好主意
It is.
打开1号气密舱
JOHANSSEN: Open A1.
- 嘿   - 嘿
Hi. Hey.
你拿好了？   - 嗯
You got it? Mmm.
引爆的时候，你要确保离开这里
Make sure you're not in here when this thing goes off.
嘿
Hey-
出舱的时候
Be careful out there.
小心点
In space.
不要告诉别人
Don't tell anyone I did that.
安装完毕
Bomb set. (BEEPING)
正在离开
Leaving Airlock 1.
各位，我计算了数据
MARTINEZ: Guys, I'm running the numbers,
就算采取这个措施
and even with optimal VAL blow...
对接角度也有问题
we're gonna be off on our angle.
约翰森，目前对接高度差是多少？
What's the intercept distance? Johanssen?
大概260米
260 meters, approximate.
太远了
That's too far.
(GROANS)
队长？
Commander?
马丁内兹，把门关上
Martinez, close the door.
打开D3
Open D3.
一直开着
And leave it open.
(GROANS)
打开B2
Open B2.
约翰森
Johanssen...
炸弹启动后多久爆炸？
Time to VAL blow after initiate?
15秒
15 seconds.
我们可真会卡时间
We sure know how to cut it close.
队长？
Commander?
距离太远，我亲自行动
Distance is too far. I'm going out.
我可以的
I can do this.
不用争论了
It's not a debate.
我不会再让你们冒险的
I'm not risking another crew member.
贝克回来了
Beck's returned.
约翰森，启动炸弹
Johanssen, initiate the bomb.
倒计时10秒
Ten seconds.
系好安全带
Strap in.
5，4
JOHANSSEN: Five, four...
(BEEPING RAPIDLY)
three...
准备好减速冲击  - 2
Brace for deceleration. JOHANSSEN: two...
one.
激活程序启动
Activating Panel 41.
(ALARM BLARING)
舱桥已封闭
Bridge seal holding.
损坏程度如何？
What's the damage?
先不管这个
LEWIS: Worry about that later.
现在的相对速度是多少？
What's the relative velocity?
12米每秒
12 meters per second.
收到
LEWIS: Copy.
挂起来
Hook me up.
好了
BECK: Done.
我能看到飞行器了
I have visual on the MAV.
距离有多远？
What's the intercept range?
计算中
JOHANSSEN: I'm checking.
312米
312 meters.
你是说312米吗？
Did you say 312?
太好了，我会向你们挥手再见的
Great. I'll wave at you guys as I go by.
哦！
(GROANS) on!
你离我太远了，马克
I can't get to you, Mark. You're too far.
我恐怕过不去了
I'm not gonna make it.
我知道
I know.
贝克，解开扣子，我去追他
LEWIS: Beck, unhook me. I'm going after him.
队长，还是我来吧
Commander, I got this.
马克，回答我
Mark, report.
我来了，队长
WATNEY: On my way, Commander.
糟糕
Damn it.
(GRUNTS)
约翰森，我和马克的相对速度是多少？
Johanssen, what's my relative velocity to Mark?
5.2米每秒
5.2 meters per second.
收到，调整方向中
Copy. Adjusting course.
现在是3.1米每秒
JOHANSSEN: 3.1 meters per second.
距目标24米
Distance to target, 24 meters.
距目标11米
11 meters to target.
6米
Six meters.
抓住，马克
(STRAINING) Hold On, Mark.
(GRUNTING)
我抓住他了
l got him.
(PANTING)
(GASPS)
我抓住他了
I got him. (ALL LAUGHING IN RELIEF)
I got him.
好样的，钢铁侠
Way to go, Iron Man.
贝克，拉我们回去
Beck, pull us in.
见到你真好
(PANTING) It's good to see you.
你的…
You...
音乐品味真是太差了
have terrible taste in music.
(BOTH LAUGHING)
休斯顿，这里是赫尔墨斯号
JOHANSSEN: Houston, this is Hermes actual.
我们成功了
We got him.
(WHOOPS) (ALL CHEERING)
沃特尼安全了
Watney is secure.
(ALL CHEERING)
太空拯救马克·沃特尼计划成功
REPORTER 1: Contact in outer space with Mark Watney.
在长期的努力后
After a very long time, they have done
他们完成了不可能的壮举
what many people thought was impossible.
再次确认
Mission confirmation:
马克·沃特尼被成功营救
Mark Watney has been successfully rescued.
(FEMALE REPORTER SPEAKING MANDARIN)
过来接住他
LEWIS: Grab a hold of him.
嘿，帅哥！
Hey, handsome!
贝克，关闭舱口
Beck, close the hatch.
嘿，大家好！
Hey, guys!
休斯顿，6名成员全部安全登舱
LEWIS: Houston, six crew safely aboard.
这是整个国家，整个世界的伟大时刻
This is huge moment for this nation, for the world...
更是国际星际航行的伟大成功
and indeed, for international space travel.
没想到你的烂计划成功了
LEWIS: I can't believe anything you do works.
嘿！
Hey!
天啊
Oh, God.
不敢相信
JOHANSSEN: I can't believe it.
伙计，你身上的味道不太好闻啊
There's a little smell going on over there, bud.
我知道，我已经一年半没洗澡了
I know. I haven't had a shower in a year and a half.
别再逗我笑了，我的肋骨断掉了
Don't make me laugh, I have broken ribs.
你好啊，小家伙
Hey, there.
- 早上好，先生- 很荣幸见到您，先生
Morning, sir. It's an honor, sir.
先生好
Sir.
- 先生好- 先生好
Sir. Sir.
早上好，先生
MALE CADET: Morning, sir.
第一天
(INDISTINCT CONVERSATIONS)
欢迎来到宇航员选拔项目
WATNEY: Welcome to the Astronaut Candidate Program.
请注意听讲
Now pay attention,
因为我的话可能会救你一命
because this could save your life.
相信我，我有亲身体验
Trust me, I know what I'm talking about.
(ALL LAUGH)
正式开始前我先说两句话
Let me get a few things out of the way, right off the bat.
没错，我是在火星
Yes, I did in fact survive on a deserted planet
靠屎种地活了下来
by farming in my own shit.
没错，这个事情比你听起来要糟的多
Yes, it's actually worse than it sounds.
所以以后就别再提了
So let's not talk about that ever again.
还有我经常被问到
The other question I get most frequently is...
当我孤身一人在火星上
"When I was up there, stranded by myself...
有没有想过会死在那里？
"did I think I was going to die?"
答案是，当然想过
Yes, absolutely.
你们参加这个项目，也要知道这点
And that's what you need to know going in
因为这很有可能发生在你们身上
because it's going to happen to you.
我们谈论的是太空，太空不会配合你工作
This is space. It does not cooperate.
有时候，所有的情况都会对你不利
At some point, everything is going to go south on you.
所有的坏事一起发生
Everything is going to go south
你就可能会想，就是这样了
and you're going to say, "This is it.
这就是我的终点了
"This is how I end."
面对这种情况，你要么接受
Now, you can either accept that...
要么想办法解决
or you can get to work.
这就是一切的真谛
That's all it is.
解决问题
You just begin.
你想各种办法，解决一个问题
You do the math. You solve one problem...
然后接着解决下一个问题
then you solve the next one.
循环往复
And then the next.
等你解决了足够多的问题
And if you solve enough problems,
你就可以回家了
you get to come home.
好了，大家有问题吗？
All right, questions?
(LOVE TRAIN PLAYING)
等指挥中心完成
ANNIE: Once Mission Control completes
起飞前检查
their pre-flight checks...
就可以开始发射流程
we'll begin launch procedures.
战神5号的团队将在发射约48分钟后
The Ares 5 team will rendezvous with the Hermes...
到达赫尔墨斯号飞船地点
approximately 48 minutes after launch.
在那里，他们即将开始
From there, they will have 414 days
长达414天的太空旅行
of space travel ahead of them.
从以前的任务到战神5号，
FEMALE REPORTER: Have the goals changed
任务的目标一直相同
from the previous mission...
还是在不断变化？
to the Ares 5 program?
这次任务的目标又是什么？
And what do you hope to achieve this time around?
对于战神任务来说，
VINCENT: Well, no. The goals have always been the same
目标一直都是相同的
for the Ares program.
这次，我们希望
This time, of course, we hope to bring
所有的宇航员能一起回来
all the astronauts back at the same time.
(REPORTERS LAUGHING)
指挥官，导航检查完毕
Flight, Guidance check complete.
收到,导航员
BRENDAN: Copy, Guidance.
我是指挥官
This is Flight.
按计划，准备发射
We are go for launch, on schedule.
(INDISTINCT RADIO CHATTER)
舱体表面
MALE REPORTER ON TV: Final aerosurface
检查完毕
checks are complete...
所有程序就绪，准备发射
as everything remains a go for the launch of the Ares 5.
倒计时20秒
20 seconds.
进入倒计时
MISSION CONTROL TECHNICIAN: Proceeding with the count.
10，9
T-minus 10... 9...
主引擎启动
Main engine start.
7，6，5，4
7... 6... 5... 4...
3，2，1
three... two... one.
发射，战神5号成员
MALE REPORTER: And liftoff. As the crew of the Ares 5...
即将开始美国太空探索的新篇章
begin the next chapter of American space exploration.
压力指数良好
MISSION CONTROL TECHNICIAN: Pressures look good.
(ALL CHEERING)
(WHOOPS)
(INDISTINCT RADIO CHATTER)
哇，好球
Wow. Good shot.
就这样
MALE REPORTER ON TV: There you have it.
在拯救马克·沃特尼行动五年之后
Five years after the rescue of astronaut Mark Watney...
战神5号即将飞往火星
an Ares 5 is on its way to Mars.
TLF字幕组欢迎你
翻译：Lilycheng        校对：Lilycheng  NetAdmin
TLF字幕组作品首发尽在http://bbs.eastgame.org
TLF中文字幕站 http://sub.eastgame.org
微博地址：http://weibo.com/tlfsubs
豆瓣小站：http://site.douban.com/127446/
人人网公共主页：http://page.renren.com/601242953
谢谢观赏
(I WILL SURVIVE PLAYING)
BMG: 葛洛莉雅·盖诺－我会活下去
BMG: Gloria Gaynor－I Will Survive
起初我很害怕，
First I was afraid
不知所措
I was petrified
一直在想：没有你在身边，我一定活不下去
Kept thinking I could never live without you by my side
但是后来，我花了很多个夜晚
But then I spent so many nights
思考你是如何辜负了我
Thinking how you did me wrong
我变得坚强 ，学会了独立
And I grew strong and I learned how to get along
然而，你从外头回到了这里
And so you're back from outer space
我走进来，
I just walked in to find you here
发现了满脸愁容的你
With that sad look upon your face
我早该换门锁
I should have changed that stupid lock
我早该叫你把钥匙留下
I should have made you leave your key
如果我早知道
If I had known for just one second
你会回来骚扰我的话
You'd be back to bother me
走吧！滚到外面去
Boy, now go, walk out the door
请你转身离开，你已经不受欢迎
Just turn around now 'cause you're not welcome anymore
你就是那个用分手来伤害我的家伙 ?
Weren't you the one who tried to hurt me with goodbye?
你以为我搞砸了?
Did you think I'd crumble?
你以为我会坐以待毙 ?
Did you think I'd lay down and die?
哦！不，我会活下去
Oh, no, not I I will survive
一旦我学会如何去爱，
For as long as I know how to love
我就能活下去
I know I'll stay alive
我会用一生好好过日子
I've got all my life to live
我会用全部的爱去奉献，
And I've got all my love to give
我会活下去
And I'll survive
I will survive
嘿, 嘿
Hey, hey
走吧！滚到外面去
Boy, now go, walk out the door
请你转身离开，你已经不受欢迎
Just turn around now 'cause you're not welcome anymore
你就是那个用分手来伤害我的家伙?
Weren't you the one who tried to break me with goodbye?
你以为我搞砸了?
Did you think I'd crumble?
你以为我会坐以待毙?
Did you think I'd lay down and die?
哦！不，我会活下去
Oh, no, not I I will survive
一旦我学会如何去爱
For as long as I know how to love
我就能活下去
I know I'll stay alive
我会用一生好好过日子
I've got all my life to live
我会用全部的爱去奉献
And I've got all my love to give
我会活下去
And I'll survive
I will survive